<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<grades>
  <socialMedia>
    <media name="facebook" username="a" password="b"></media>
    <media name="twitter" username="" passoword=""></media>
    <media name="instagram" username="" password=""></media>
  </socialMedia>
  <certificates>
    <ach name="Improve 25% in grade 5 fractions!" date="06/06/2020" socialMedia="facebook,instagram"></ach>
    <ach name="Score 90% in grade 5 integers!" date="06/07/2020" socialMedia="twitter"></ach>
    <ach name="scored 90% in placeValue" date="5/8/2020 12:00:00 AM" socialMedia="" />
  </certificates>
  <goldRuberg></goldRuberg>
  <games>
    <type name="Multiplayer Game" level="5" score="">
      <game name="Four Operations" score=""></game>
    </type>
    <type name="Tournament" level="5" score="">
      <game name="Science Tournament" level="5" score=""></game>
      <game name="Math Tournament" level="5" score=""></game>
    </type>
    <type name="Competition" level="5" score="">
      <game name="Gold Ruberg compeition" level="5" score=""></game>
      <game name="Rocket launching competition" level="5" score=""></game>
    </type>
    <type name="Single Player Game" level="5" score="">
      <game name="Four Operations" level="" score=""></game>
      <game name="Recycling" level="" score=""></game>
    </type>
    <type name="Custom Game" level="5" score="">
      <game name="Join game" level="" score=""></game>
      <game name="Host game" level="" score=""></game>
    </type>
  </games>
  <grade number="tutorial">
    <subject name="simple">
      <model>
        <simple>Welcome!</simple>
        <advanced>This tutorial will walk you through the basics of the Dive platform, and show you everything you need to know</advanced>
        <advanced>But first, we would like to tell you how our platform was designed to help you learn.</advanced>
        <advanced>At Dive, it doesn't matter where you start, or how quickly you learn the materials. All that matters is that everyday you learn and discover a little more than the day before!</advanced>
        <advanced>It is important to realize that making mistakes is apart of any learning process. At Dive you will not be punished for mistakes.</advanced> //fix this
        <advanced>So, let's Dive In!</advanced></model>
      <model>
        <simple>Student Menu</simple>
        <advanced>This is the home menu for Dive. From here you will be able to visit and do a variety of things, let's go throught them!</advanced>
        <advanced>To continue, simply click the blue box</advanced>
      </model>
      <model>
        <simple>Your Character</simple>
        <advanced>This is your customizable Dive character. You can change him/her however you like! If you wan to add a little extra you can buy him gear from the Dive shop!</advanced>
      </model>
      <model>
        <simple>Dive Level</simple>
        <advanced>As you begin to earn more Dive points from learning and exploring, you will begin to level up!</advanced>
        <advanced>As you level up, you will have access to better prizes, and earn more Dive points!</advanced>
      </model>
      <model>
        <simple>Dive Points</simple>
        <advanced>As you learn and discover more, you will be rewarded with Dive points. You can use Dive points to purchase things from the shop!</advanced>
      </model>
      
      //shop
      <model><simple>Prize Teir</simple><advanced>Here you can spend your well-earned Dive points! Prizes in the shop are put into three teirs, with Teir 3 being the best prizes!</advanced><advanced>Remember, the more you save the better prizes you can earn!</advanced><advanced>To buy a prize, simply click on the prize you wish to buy</advanced></model>
      
      //shop with popup
      <model><simple>Popup</simple><advanced>When you wish to buy a prize, you will have to confirm your selection here.</advanced><advanced>When you click OK, if you have enought Dive points you will have bought the prize, and depending on what you bought it will be sent/shipped/given to you</advanced><advanced>To return to the homemenu, simply click the Back button</advanced></model>
      //student menu
      <model><simple>Student Information</simple><advanced>To see how much you've learned, and see what you need to keep improving on, click the Student Information button</advanced></model>
      //mod for student info
      
      <model><simple>Subjects</simple><advanced>Here you will have to select which subject you want to see your results and scores in, click on Math to continue</advanced></model><model><simple>Test Scores</simple><advanced>In the test score section, you are able to see all of your past test scores for this subject. There are always 3 tests, the Placment, Progress and Final test</advanced><advanced>But remember, these tests are only meant to help us find what you need more work on, and for you to see improvment in that subject</advanced><advanced>If you've improved between tests, this is shown with a green arrow and green text, otherwise itis a red arrow and red text</advanced></model><model><simple>Past Quizes</simple><advanced>In this panel you can see all of your past quiz scores. You can find exactly which topics you are struggling with, and which one's you know well.</advanced><advanced>You can take tests and quizes as many times as you like with no penalty. In the graph only the most recent scores are shown, to see all of your past scores click on the bar you are interested in</advanced></model>
      //breakdown
      <model><simple>Breakdown</simple><advanced>In this page, you can see all of you past scores for that test or quiz.</advanced><advanced>This way you can see improvment as you learn and understand more!</advanced><advanced>To return to the Student Information page, click the Back button</advanced></model>
      //student info
      <model><simple>Back to Student Menu</simple><advanced>To return to the homemenu, click the Back button</advanced></model>
      //studnet menu
      <model><simple>Learn something new</simple><advanced>To start a new lesson, click on the Learn something new button</advanced></model>
      //mod menu
      <model><simple>Home Menu</simple><advanced>Here you can select which grade, and which subject you would like to learn!</advanced><advanced>The grades are from five to ten. Each grade has the same subjects: Math, science and other</advanced><advanced>In the "other" button, subjects, such as history or social science are taught</advanced><advanced>To continue, click on the Math button</advanced></model>
      //math mod
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>Here you can choose exactly which topic you would like to learn.</advanced><advanced>You can see exactly which topics you've done, and what your score on the quizes where. Remember, you can always go back to a topic to learn and practice more!</advanced><advanced>Click on the Addition and Subtraction button to continue</advanced></model>
      //math menu
      <model><simple>Math</simple><advanced>Here you can learn and practice math. There are few different ways to answer questions, lets go throught them!</advanced><advaanced>The question is shown at the top of the screen. You will be given a few different ways to answer the question below</advaanced><advanced>Currently, the number bar is showing. To enter the answer you will need to click on the numbers "3" and "1"</advanced><advanced>click on the number bar to continue</advanced></model>
      //math menu with answer enterd, and right answer showing
      <model><simple>Correct answer</simple><advanced>When you get a correct answer, the question counter on the right side will increase, and the next question will be shown</advanced><advanced>The question counter shows you how many questions you have answered, and how many questions you have left</advanced><advanced>Below, is a different type of way to enter the answer, click on the box to continue</advanced></model>
      //drag and drop
      <model><simple>Drag and Drop</simple><advanced>Here, you can to sort the numbers. To do this, simply click on the box you want to place, and click in any of the empty places</advanced><advanced>If you make a mistake, simply click on the box and it will return to the top</advanced><advanced>When all the numbers are sorted, the next question will be shown</advanced></model>
      //multiple choice
      <model><simple>Multiple Choice</simple><advanced>Here, to answer the question you will need to click on the right multiple choice answer</advanced><advanced>When you've finished all the questions in the section, there's a quick mini-quiz. This quiz is only meant to help you see how much you've learned, and if you need some more practice!</advanced></model>
      //quiz 
      <model><simple>Quiz</simple><advanced>After finishing each topic, there is a small quiz. You have 5 minutes to answer 10 questions. The timer is on the right side of the screen</advanced><advanced>After you've finished the 10 questions</advanced></model>
      //game
      <model><simple>Game</simple><advanced>Sometimes after a quiz, there is a quick game to help you take a break! </advanced><advanced>There are many different games, and these are covered in the advanced tutorial at the end</advanced></model>
//math mod
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>When you are finished with your math lesson, simply scroll down and click the Back button to return to the Home Menu</advanced></model>
      //home menu
      <model><simple>Home Menu</simple><advanced>Back in the Home Menu, you can choose to learn a different subject, in this case lets choose science</advanced></model>
      //science mod
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>Here, you can choose from a variety of science modules. The menu is similar to the one for math, simply click on one of the topics to learn it</advanced><advanced>There are a few different ways that science is taught, lets explore!</advanced></model>
      //model (maybe just use planets)
      <model><simple>Models</simple><advanced>Here, the material is taught using visual 3d models. Each model is interactive, simply click on it to select it </advanced><advanced>When a model is collected, its name is shown at the top, and an animation is shown to see the model in more detail</advanced><advanced>To learn more about the model, click it again. This will pull up the information panel for the model</advanced><advanced>Make sure you click on each model! Some models have parts inside of them which are also clickable, feel free to take your time and explore</advanced><advanced>When you have learned more about the models, and want to test your knowledge, click the space bar, this will bring up the menu</advanced></model>
      //menu
      <model><simple>Menu</simple><advanced>This is the menu. This menu can be accessed from any learning module, by clicking the space bar</advanced><advanced>To start the quiz click the Start Quiz button</advanced></model>
      //model quiz
      <model><simple>Quiz</simple><advanced>In the quiz there are two different types of questions, in the first type the question is shown at the top, and you can click on the model which answers the question</advanced><advanced>Click on the model to continue</advanced></model>
      //table 
      <model><simple>Quiz</simple><advanced>The second type of question only shows the names of the models, and you must answer the question by clicking on the button</advanced><advanced>Click on the button to continue</advanced></model>
      //science mod
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>Lets explore one of the other ways to learn science! Click on the button to continue</advanced></model>
      //database
      <model><simple>Image Question</simple><advanced>Here you can learn more about subjects using visual pictures </advanced><advanced>To continue, click on the image</advanced></model><model><simple></simple><advanced></advanced></model>
      //science mod
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>When you are finished with your science lesson, simply scroll down and click on the Back button</advanced></model>
      //home menu
      <model><simple>Home Menu</simple><advanced>Finally, lets explore the Virtual presentaiton module</advanced><advanced>For this module to work best, you will need the Dive Headset and Dive Controller, both of which can be bouth online at DiveVr.org</advanced><advanced>To continue, click on the button</advanced></model>
      //presentation
      <model><simple>Module Menu</simple><advanced>Here, you can choose a variety of locations to practice your public speaking.</advanced><advanced>Click on the location to continue</advanced></model>
      //presentation
      <model><simple>Presentation</simple><advanced>Welcome to the Virtual Presentation module! Here you can practice and perfect your public speaking skills</advanced><advanced>The module helps you keep track of your filler words (like, uhm, basically), your eye-contact with the audience, and the tone of your speach</advanced>//ok so add how it works, and how to practice with it and use it
        <advanced>You can use this module to practice a school presentation, a job interview, or just speaking skills in general</advanced><advanced>Click on the button to continue</advanced></model><model> //tell them about the results 
        <simple>Results</simple><advanced>After every speech the results are shown. First, the results show you you're use of filler words. </advanced><advanced>Click on the button to continue</advanced></model>
      //reults 2
      <model> //and then done 
        <simple>Filler Words</simple><advanced>The hard part about filler words is we often use them without even realizing.</advanced><advanced>The graph below shows the most common filler words, and how many of each you used in your speach</advanced><advanced>Click the button to continue</advanced></model><model><simple>Eye Contact</simple><advanced>This pie graph shows the amount of eyecontact you gave each person in your audience. With the grey part representing no eye contact</advanced><advancd>Click the button to continue</advancd></model><model><simple>Tone</simple><advanced>Finally, you need to choose which tones you wanted to convey with your speech. The selected tones are feelings that you wanted your speech to cause your audience</advanced><advanced>When you've choosen your tones simply click the button to continue</advanced></model><model><simple>Tone Graph</simple><advanced>This graph shows you how well you're speech's tone matched with the tones you wished to convey</advanced><advanced>The way the scoring works is it rewards you if your audience felt the tones you wanted them to feel, and takes away points if they didn't feel any of the tones you wanted them to, or felt a tone you didn't want them to</advanced><advanced>Remember, the tone is from the words in the speech itself, not necessarly how you say it</advanced><advanced>Click the button to continue</advanced></model><model><simple>Results</simple><advanced>Finally, all of your results are summarized on this page. The results can be seen anytime by going to the Student Information menu, and selecting Presentations</advanced><advanced>Click the button to continue</advanced></model><model><simple>Done!</simple><advanced>We hope you enjoyed the tour of Dive! Remember, the actual app will look and feel different, but the features will be the same</advanced><advanced>If you would like to continue to learn more about other features, such as Games, or competitions, click on the Advanced Tutorial button, otherwise, click the exit button</advanced><advanced>Have fun and Bon Voyage!</advanced></model></subject>
    <subject name="advanced">
      <model>
        <simple></simple>
        <advanced></advanced>
      </model>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="5">
    <subject name="math">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
      <test name="placement test" topics="23,25,59,20" level="5" index="12" score="3/16/2020,120,76 3/17/2020,100,56 3/18/2020,90,56"></test>
      <lesson name="placeValue" topics="103,104,105,9,107,106" level="5" index="0" score="3/16/2020,120,76"></lesson>
      <lesson name="addition and subtraction" topics="1,2" level="5" index="1" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="multiplication" topics="3,6" level="5" index="2" score="3/18/2020,90,56"></lesson>
      <lesson name="division" topics="4,5" level="5" index="3" score="3/16/2020,120,76"></lesson>
      <lesson name="number theory" topics="116,114,115,15,16,17,18,10,108" level="5" index="4" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="add subtract decimals" topics="125" level="8" index="5" score="3/17/2020,100,56"></lesson>
      <lesson name="operations with decimals" topics="127" level="7" index="6" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="money" topics="24,25,53" level="5" index="7" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="fractions and mixed numbers" topics="7,59" level="5" index="8" score="0"></lesson> //this one is converting between fractions and mixed //77-81 is fdp stuff, //54 is fraction 4 ops 
      <lesson name="fractions equivalence and ordering" topics="42,20,28" level="5" index="9" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="add subtract fractions" topics="31" level="5" index="10" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="multiply and divide fractions" topics="32" level="5" index="11" score="0"></lesson><test name="progress check" topics="23,20,24,31" level="5" index="12" score="3/18/2020,90,76"></test><lesson name="roman numbers" topics="129,130" level="5" index="102" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="paterns and sequences" topics="71,21,47" level="5" index="14" score="0"></lesson> //71 fibb 72 geometric   21 nth term linear  22 nth term generating  sequ 47 
      <lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132" level="5" index="15" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="variable expresions" topics="68,64,65,29,51,30" level="5" index="16" score="0"></lesson> //simplyfying ratios 19
 //one step 29   number bonds 30   two step 38,   three step 43  equa mixed 44   equ with brackets 46   equ with brackets both 48   sub 51 
      <lesson name="probability and statistics" topics="33,34,35,36,58,63" level="5" index="18" score="0"></lesson> //multiply terms 64   single brackets 65   expand simplify brackets 66     one, two, three step 68,69,70
      <lesson name="time" topics="74,112,110,111,26" level="5" index="19" score="0"></lesson> //74 converting time  26 speed dist time    110 elapsed time   time problem 111  converting time 112 
      <lesson name="units of measurement" topics="55,56,57,45,74,112,61" level="5" index="20" score="0"></lesson>  //weight 55  volume 56  mixed 57   45 length   74 time  convertin time 112
      <lesson name="two-dimensional figures" topics="141,142,143,144,62" level="5" index="21" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="angles" topics="140,143" level="5" index="103" score="0"></lesson> //replace these with 
      <lesson name="three-dimensional figures" topics="149,150" level="5" index="23" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132" level="5" index="26" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="expressions and properties" topics="68,64,65,29,51,30" index="16" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="one-variable equations" topics="29,38,64,65,68,51,66,44" level="5" index="33" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="ratios and rates" topics="92,93,94,12,52,19" level="5" index="31" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="problem solving and estimation" topics="109" level="5" index="13" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="percents" topics="8,49,50,13,95,96,67,97" level="5" index="32" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="linear functions" topics="82,83,145,146,147,148" level="5" index="44" score="0"></lesson><test name="final exam" topics="23,31,32,112,140" level="5" index="12" score="3/18/2020,90,66"></test></subject>
    //not used
    <lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="geometic measurment" topics="-1" level="5" index="24" score="0"></lesson>  //45 converting length
    <subject name="science"><lesson name="Matter and mass" topics="1" level="5" index="62" inq="Can you think of some compounds and elements we use everyday? Write your answers below!" score="0"><model section="1"><simple>Matter</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about what matter, atoms, bonds, compounds and subatomic particles</advanced><advanced>Matter is the substance of which all material is made. That means objects which have mass. More specifically, they must have rest mass, which is a form of energy that matter has even when it is not moving</advanced><advanced>In addition to its rest mass, matter can contain other forms of energy, which aren't matter but allow them to interact with each other by exchanging kinetic energy, heat, light, sound waves, etc.</advanced><advanced>Matter can be directly experienced through the senses. It has properties which can be measured, such as mass, volume, density, and qualitative properties such as taste, smell and colour, for instance.</advanced></model><model><simple>Bonds</simple><advanced>All atoms would like to have a full outer shell, but the only elements to naturally have a full outer shell are the noble gases to the right of the periodic table. As a result, when atoms without full outer shells come into contact with other atoms, they tend to want to give up or gain electrons, this is called bonding</advanced><advanced>The valence electrons are the number of electrons in an outer shell of an atom that can participate in forming chemical bonds with other atoms.</advanced><advanced>There are two general types of bonds that atoms can form: Ionic and covalent</advanced><advanced>Ionic bonding occurs when one element donates an electron (or electrons) to another so that both elements will have a full outer shell.</advanced><advanced>In covalent bonding electrons are shared between atoms rather than donated in order for the atoms of both elements to gain full outer shells. Electrons are always shared in pairs.</advanced><advanced>After bonding, the atoms become more stable then before, and their energy levels become lower</advanced><quiz>This happens between the valence (outer) shell of electrons of two or more atoms</quiz></model><model><simple>Hydrogen</simple><advanced>Hydrogen is the first element in the periodic table. It is the simplest possible atom composed of one proton in the nucleus which is orbited by a single electron. Hydrogen is the lightest of the elements and is the most abundant element in the universe.</advanced><advanced>At standard temperature and pressure hydrogen is a colorless, odorless, and tasteless gas.</advanced><advanced>Hydrogen is very flammable and burns with an invisible flame. It burns when it comes into contact with oxygen. The byproduct of a hydrogen and oxygen explosion is water.</advanced><quiz>This is the first element in the periodic table</quiz></model><model><simple>Oxygen</simple><advanced>Oxygen is an element with the chemical symbol O and atomic number 8. Under standard temperature and pressure conditions two oxygen atoms join to form dioxygen (O2), a colorless, tasteless and odorless gas.</advanced><advanced>Oxygen is a very reactive element that easily forms compounds such as oxides.</advanced><advanced>Oxygen is essential to human life, it is found in the air we breathe and the water we drink (H20).</advanced><quiz>This element has chemical Symbol O</quiz><quiz>This elment is very reactive, and easily forms compounds such as oxides</quiz></model><model><simple>Compounds</simple><advanced>A compound is a type of molecule with more than one element.</advanced><advanced>Chemical compounds are formed when elements are joined by chemical bonds. These bonds are so strong that the compound behaves like a single substance. Compounds have their own properties that are unique from the elements they are made of. </advanced><quiz>This is a type of molecule with one or more elements. </quiz><quiz>This is formed when elements are joined together by chemical bonds</quiz></model><model><simple>Electron cloud</simple><advanced>The electron is a negatively charged particle that spins around the outside of the nucleus.</advanced><advanced>Electrons spin so fast around the nucleus, scientists can never be 100% sure where they are located, therefore they are said to exist in shells</advanced><advanced>Each shell can only contain a certain number of electrons: the first layer can hold two electrons, the second layer eight electrons, the third layer eighteen electrons, etc.</advanced><advanced> If there are the same number of electrons and protons in an atom, then the atom is said to have a neutral charge. </advanced><advanced>Electons have a mass of about 1/2000 of a proton, therefore, we say that they do not affect the mass of the atom, however, they're charge is equally as strong as that of a proton</advanced><quiz>This part of the atom has a negative charge</quiz><quiz>This part of the atom contains electrons that spin around the nucleus</quiz><quiz>This part of the atom doesn't affect the weight of the atom</quiz></model><model><simple>Nucleus</simple><advanced>The nucleus contains two types of smaller particles. Protons which have a positive charge and neutrons which have a neutral charge. Protons are the reason why a nucleus has a positive charge.</advanced><quiz>This is the central part of the atom</quiz><quiz>This part of the atom consists of neutrons and protons</quiz><quiz>This part of the atom has an overall positive charge</quiz></model><model><simple>Atom</simple><advanced>The atom is the basic building block for all matter in the universe. Atoms are extremely small and are made up of a few even smaller particles. </advanced><advanced>Every atom can be thought of as a circular shape with two parts: a nucleus and electrons</advanced><advanced>The nucleus is found at the centre of every atom and has a positive charge.  Negatively charged electrons surround the nucleus and it's these two opposite charges that hold an atom together. </advanced><quiz>This is the building block of all matter in the universe</quiz></model><model><simple>Neutron</simple><advanced>The neutron doesn't have any charge. The number of neutrons affects the mass and the radioactivity of the atom.</advanced><quiz>This subatomic particle has no charge</quiz><quiz>This subatomic particle affects the mass, but not the charge of the atom</quiz></model><model><simple>Proton</simple><advanced>The proton is a positively charged particle that is located at the center of the atom in the nucleus. The hydrogen atom is unique in that it only has a single proton and no neutron in its nucleus.</advanced><advanced>Protons also affect the mass of the atom, and have the same amount of mass of a neutron</advanced><quiz>This subatomic particle has a positive charge</quiz><quiz>Every element has this subatomic particle, found in the nucleus of the atom</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Heat and thermal energy" topics="2" level="5" index="63" inq="Can you explain why water at 20 degrees feels hotter than air at 20 degrees?" score="0"> //also have physical and chemical change 
        <model><simple>Heat and thermal energy</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the relationship between heat and thermal energy, as well as how they relate to particles and particle motion</advanced></model><model type="1" section="1"><simple>Kinetic particle theory</simple><advanced>The kinetic particle theory explains the properties of the different states of matter. </advanced><advanced>The particles in solids, liquids and gases have different amounts of energy. They are arranged differently and move in different ways.</advanced><quiz>This states that different states have different amounts of energy, and this causes them to behave and move differently</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Solid</simple><advanced>In a solid, the particles are close together, and do not move. They form a regular pattern, and vibrate in one location</advanced><advanced>In a solid's have a fixed shape and cannot flow, this is because the particles themselves are stuck in that position</advanced><advanced>Solids can also not be squished or compressed, this is because there is not space between the particles themselves</advanced><advanced>Solids can become either liquids, in a process called melting, or gasses, in a process called sublimation</advanced><quiz>This state of matter has particles close together, and is unable to change shape</quiz><quiz>This state of matter has particles vibrating in only one location</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Liquid</simple><advanced>In a liquid the particles are close together, in a random arrangment and can move around eachother</advanced><advanced>Liquids flow and take the shape of their container, this is because the particles themselves are free to move around and flow</advanced><advanced>Liquids cannot be squished or compressed, this is because the particles themselves are close together, and there is not space for them to be compressed into</advanced><advanced>Liquids can become solids in a process called freezing, or a gas in a process called boiling</advanced><advanced>Boiling is not to be confused with evaporation, they are differentin the following ways: evaporation can occur at any temperature - not just the boiling point, it only happens at the surface of the liquid - 
          not throughout like boiling, and finally boiling requires energy, whereas evaportaion is the release of the highest energy particles</advanced><quiz>This state of matter has particles close together, however, they are able to change shape</quiz><quiz>This state of matter can both freeze, boil and evaporate</quiz><quiz>This state of matter takes the shape of the container it is in, and is unable to be compressed</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Brownian motion</simple><advanced>Particles in both liquids and gases (collectively called fluids) move randomly. This is called Brownian motion. They do this because they are bombarded by the other moving particles in the fluid. Larger particles can be moved by light, fast-moving molecules.</advanced><advanced>Brownian motion is named after the botanist Robert Brown, who first observed this in 1827. He used a microscope to look at pollen grains moving randomly in water. At this point, he could not explain why this occurred.</advanced><advanced>But in 1905, physicist Albert Einstein explained that the pollen grains were being moved by individual water molecules. This confirmed that atoms and molecules did exist, and provided evidence for particle theory.</advanced><quiz>This states that particles move randomly</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Gas</simple><advanced>In a gas the particles are far apart, in a random arrangment, and they move quickly in all directions</advanced><advanced>Gasses flow and completly fill their container, this is becasue the particles can quickly move in all directions, and try to spread out as much as possible</advanced><advanced>Gasses can be squished and compressed, this is because there is space between the particles themselves</advanced><quiz>In this state of matter, the particles are far apart and move quickly</quiz><quiz>In this state of matter particles can be compressed</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Thermal expansion</simple><advanced>All three states of matter (solid, liquid and gas) expand when heated. The atoms themselves do not expand, but the volume they take up does.</advanced><advanced>When a solid is heated, its atoms vibrate faster about their fixed points. The relative increase in the size of solids when heated is therefore small. </advanced><advanced>Liquids expand for the same reason, but because the bonds between separate molecules are usually less tight they expand more than solids. </advanced><advanced>Molecules within gases are further apart and weakly attracted to each other. Heat causes the molecules to move faster, (heat energy is converted to kinetic energy) which means that the volume of a gas increases more than the volume of a solid or liquid.</advanced><quiz>This states that all states of matter expand when heated</quiz></model><model type="2" section="1"><simple>Specific latent heat</simple><advanced>The specific latent heat of a substance is a measure of how much heat energy is needed to melt or boil it. It is the energy needed to melt or boil 1 kg of the substance.</advanced><advanced>Different substances have different specific latent heats. The specific latent heat of a given substance is different for boiling than it is for melting.  For example the specific latent heat of water is 
          334 kJ/kg for melting, while for boiling it is 2260 kJ/kg. (kJ means kilo joules, which is the same as 1000 Joules. Joules is a unit of energy)</advanced><advanced>Here is the equation that relates energy to specific latent heat: energy (J) = mass (kg) × specific latent heat (J/kg)</advanced><advanced>The latent heat of melting is sometimes called the latent heat of fusion, while the latent heat of boiling is sometimes called the latent heat of vaporisation. </advanced><quiz>This measures the amount of energy needeed to melt or boil a substance</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Physical and chemical change" topics="3" level="5" index="64" inq="Can you think of some checmical changes we see everyday?" score="0"><model><simple>Physical and chemical change</simple><advanced>In this module you wil learn about the difference between physical and chemical change. And how they can occur</advanced><advanced>By the end of this module you will </advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Mixtures" topics="4" level="5" index="65" inq="Sometimes concentrations can make a big difference, can you think of two everyday mixtures that have the same substances but different concentrations? How are they different/similar?" score="0"><model><simple>Forming mixtures</simple><advanced>One of the main aspects of chemistry is combining different substances. Sometimes combining substances can cause a chemical reaction and bonding which creates an entirely new substance called a compound.</advanced><advanced>However, sometimes there is no chemical reaction or bonding. In this case, a mixture is formed from the combined substances.</advanced></model><model><simple>Mixtures</simple><advanced>A mixture is made when two or more substances are combined, but they are not combined chemically.</advanced><advanced> General properties of a mixture: The components of a mixture can be easily separated, the components each keep their original properties, the proportion of the components is variable</advanced><quiz>This is formed when two or more substances are combined, physically but not chemically</quiz></model><model><simple>Types of mixtures</simple><advanced>There are two main categories of mixtures: homogeneous mixtures and heterogeneous mixtures. </advanced><advanced>In a homogenous mixture all the substances are evenly distributed throughout the mixture (salt water, air, blood).</advanced><advanced>In a heterogeneous mixture the substances are not evenly distributed (chocolate chip cookies, pizza, rocks)</advanced><advanced>Within the categories of homogeneous and heterogeneous mixtures there are more specific types of mixtures including solutions, alloys, suspensions, and colloids.</advanced></model> //these three are timed 
        
        
        <model> //these ones show up when you change the dropdown
          <simple>Solutions</simple><advanced>A solution is a mixture where one of the substances dissolves in the other. The substance that dissolves is called the solute. The substance that does not dissolve is called the solvent.</advanced><advanced>An example of a solution is salt water. These components can be easily separated through evaporation and they each retain their original properties. However, the salt is dissolved into the water to where you can't see it and it is evenly distributed in the water. In this example the water is the solvent and the salt is the solute.</advanced><quiz>This is a type of mixture where one substance dissolves the other</quiz><quiz>It consists of two parts, the solute and the solvent</quiz><quiz>Salt water is this type of mixture</quiz></model><model><simple>Alloys</simple><advanced>An alloy is a mixture of elements that has the characteristic of a metal. At least one of the elements mixed is a metal. One example of an alloy is steel which is made from a mixture of iron and carbon.</advanced><quiz>This is a mixture of elements that have the characteristics of a metal</quiz><quiz>At least one of the elements in this mixtures is a metal</quiz><quiz>Steel is an example of this alloy</quiz></model><model><simple>Bronze</simple><advanced>Bronze is a metal alloy. Bronze is mostly copper, with some tin added (usually between 5% and 20% tin).</advanced><advanced>Bronze was the first alloy that was used by humans. The first nation that used Bronze was Egypt about 3500 years B.C. This gave the name for the Bronze Age.</advanced><advanced>Bronze is stronger than copper or tin alone. Bronze lasts longer than copper. Pure copper can be oxidized by air and also by water. When copper is oxidized by air or water, it turns green (the color of "copper oxide"), and falls apart.</advanced><quiz>This was the first alloy used by humans</quiz><quiz>This alloy is made of copper and tin</quiz></model><model><simple>Steal</simple><advanced>Steel is a mixture of several metals but most of it is iron. Steel is harder and stronger than iron. Steels are often iron alloys with between 0.02% and 1.7% percent carbon by weight. </advanced><advanced>Steel has a long history. People in India and Sri Lanka were making small amounts of steel more than 2,500 years ago. It was very expensive and was often used to make swords and knives.</advanced><advanced> It is a very cheap metal and is used to make many things. Steel is used in making buildings and bridges, and all kinds of machines. Almost all ships and cars are today made from steel. When a steel object is old, or it is broken beyond repair, it is called scrap. It can be melted down and re-shaped into a new object. Steel is recyclable material; that is, the same steel can be used and re-used.</advanced><quiz>This is one of the most common alloys in use today, and is used in machines, building, and cars amoung other things</quiz><quiz>This alloy is made of iron and carbon</quiz></model><model><simple>Solder</simple><advanced>Solder is a metal or alloy that melts at a low temperature. here are two types of solder; soft solder and hard solder. Soft solder melts easily with soldering irons and is used for electronics and electrical work. Hard solder melts at a higher temperature with a torch.</advanced><advanced>There are two main types of soft solder; lead solder and lead-free solder. Lead solders have about 60% (or 63%) tin and 40% (or 37%) lead in them. Today lead solder is banned in many applications, because of its toxic effects</advanced><quiz>This alloy melts at very low temperaturs</quiz><quiz>This alloy is made of tin aand lead</quiz></model><model><simple>Suspensions</simple><advanced>A suspension is a mixture between a liquid and particles of a solid. In this case the particles do not dissolve. The particles and the liquid are mixed up so that the particles are dispersed throughout the liquid. They are "suspended" in the liquid. A key characteristic of a suspension is that the solid particles will settle and separate over time if left alone.</advanced><advanced>An example of a suspension is a mixture of water and sand. When mixed up, the sand will disperse throughout the water. If left alone, the sand will settle to the bottom.</advanced><quiz>If I mix water and sand, it become this kind of mixture</quiz></model><model><simple>Colloids</simple><advanced>A colloid is a mixture where very small particles of one substance are evenly distributed throughout another substance. They appear very similar to solutions, but the particles are suspended in the solution rather than fully dissolved.</advanced><advanced>The difference between a colloid and a suspension is that the particles will not settle to the bottom over a period of time, they will stay suspended or float.</advanced><quiz>This type of mixtures is similar to suspensions, but the particles do not settle over time</quiz><quiz>This type of mixture has particles suspended and spread out in the solution</quiz></model><model><simple>Concentration</simple><advanced>In chemistry, concentration is how much of a substance is mixed with another substance.</advanced><advanced>The substance that is dissolved (shown as the red dye in the example) is known as the solute. The substance in which the solute is dissolved (shown as the water in the example) is known as the solvent.</advanced><advanced>To concentrate a solution, one must add more solute, or reduce the amount of solvent. To dilute a solution, one must add more solvent, or reduce the amount of solute.</advanced><quiz>This describes the amount of a substance (the solute) that is disolved in another substance (the solvent)</quiz><quiz>This describes how dilute, or how concentrated a solution is</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Velocity, acceleration, and forces" topics="27" level="5" index="66" inq="Can you think of a new way to get to space? Describe it below!" score="0"><model><simple>Newtons laws and gravity</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about Newtons laws, and gravity. By the end of this module you will understand the basics of Newtons laws, and how they apply to the real world example of launching a rocket!</advanced><advanced>First, choose the material and the fuel you would like to use in your rocket. Then click the launch button to launch your rocket! The higher your rocket goes, the more you will learn.</advanced><advanced>To turn off the popups, simple deselect Active Learning the settings menu</advanced></model><model><simple>Steel</simple><advanced>Steel is a mixture of several metals (this is called an alloy) but most of it is iron.</advanced><advanced>Something made of pure iron is softer than steel because the atoms can slip over one another. If other atoms like carbon are added, they are different from iron atoms and stop the iron atoms from sliding apart so easily. This makes the metal stronger and harder.</advanced><advanced>Althought steel is stronger and lighter than iron, it is often not strong or light enough for use in most rockets</advanced></model><model><simple>Aluminium</simple><advanced>Aluminum is a chemical element. It is the most abundant metal, and is known for its resistance to corrosion and its light weight.</advanced><advanced> Aluminum, however, melts at the high reentry temperatures. So, if a rocket needs to come back to Earth (like the Space Shuttle), heat shield tiles are added</advanced></model><model><simple>Titanium</simple><advanced>Titanium is a very strong metal. It is chemical element number 22 on the periodic table </advanced><advanced>Titanium is used for making the strongest and lightest parts of fighter jets, aircraft, and rockets</advanced><advanced>However, it can burn at high temperatures, and titanium dust is extremely flammable. </advanced></model><model><simple>Carbon composite</simple><advanced> It has the highest compressive strength of all the reinforcing materials (composites), and it has a high strength to weight ratio and low coefficient of thermal expansion</advanced><advanced> The density of carbon fiber is also much lower than the density of steel.</advanced><advanced>Carbon fiber is in the form of several thousand long, thin strands of material that is composed of mostly carbon atoms.</advanced></model><model><simple>Spring</simple><advanced>Spring propelled rockets use the potential energy stored in a compressed spring, to form kinetic energy, and launch the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These types of rockets are easy to make at home, however, they do not go very high!</advanced></model><model><simple>Compressed air</simple><advanced>Compressed air rockets use the pressure of a compressed air tank, to form kinetic energy launching the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These systems are more powerful then spring powered ones, however, they </advanced><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Solid fuel</simple><advanced>Solid rocket fuels are those in which the fuel and oxidiser compounds are already combined.</advanced><advanced>Most use an aluminium powder as the fuel and an ammonium perchlorate as the oxidiser, while an iron powder is used as a catalyst for the reaction.</advanced><advaced>Solid fuels are generally used more for the initial launch sequence, when the speed needs to be at its maximum, whereas liquid fuels are used later so the speed can be adjusted to get the rocket’s payload on to the right trajectory.</advaced></model><model><simple>Liquid fuel</simple><advanced>Liquid propellants separate fuel and oxidisers and the two are combined in a combustion chamber where they burn and are ﬁred out from the base of the rocket.</advanced><advanced>iquid fuels are further subcategorised into either petroleum, cryogens or hypergols.</advanced><advanced>Petroleum is fuel derived from crude oil and hydrocarbons, it consists of a highly refined kerosene mixed with liquid oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Cryogens are those stored at very low temperatures (such as liquid hydrogen)</advanced><advanced>Hypergols are able to self-ignite on contact between the fuel and the oxidiser.  These fuels simply needs nitric acid in order to ignite and are frequently used for propulsion when out in space.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravity</simple><advanced>Gravity is one of the four fundamental forces of nature, althought it is the weakest of these four forces, it is important to life on Earth and the structure of the universe.</advanced><advanced>Everything that has matter generates gravity, from a grain of sand to the largest objects in the universe. The larger an object is, the stronger its force</advanced><advanced>In order for a rocket to reach space, the force it exerts up, must be more than the force of gravity pulling it down</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Third Law</simple><advanced>Rocket fuel works on the basis of Newton’s Third Law of Motion, which states that ‘every action is accompanied by an equal and opposite reaction'.</advanced><advanced>By ﬁring fuel out the back of a rocket, the force propels it upwards with acceleration equal to the force at which the fuel is expelled.</advanced><quiz>This law states that every action has an equal and opposite reaction</quiz><quiz>Rockets are based on this law, it is what causes the rocket to be pushed up, when the exahust is pushed down</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Second Law</simple><advanced>Newtons Second Law says that the acceleration of an object produced by a net (total) applied force is directly related to the magnitude of the force, the same direction as the force, and inversely related to the mass of the object</advanced><quiz>This law states that aceleration is directly related to the force, and inversly related to the mass of an object</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that it is harder to push heavier things </quiz></model><model><simple>Space</simple><advanced>Space begins about 100 km (62 miles) above Earth's surface.</advanced><advanced>However, the space around Earth is not empty. There are many artificial satellites, about 5000, these are used for gather information, navigation, and communication amoung other things.</advanced><advanced>There is also a large amount of space junk. Space junk is any human-made object orbiting Earth that no longer serves a useful purpose. Scientists estimate there are about 500,000 pieces of space junk today.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons First Law</simple><advanced>Newtons First Law says that an object at rest tends to stay at rest, and an object in motion tends to stay in motion, with the same direction and speed</advanced><advanced>For example, if you watch videos of astronauts in space, you will notice that their tools float, and they wont move unless the astronaut pushes or pulls it, at which point it will keep moving until it is stopped</advanced><quiz>This law states that an object will stay at rest, or continue in motion unless acted on by an external force</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that objects stay in one spot in space</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Slower</simple><quiz>If a rocket was launched from jupiter, (where the gravity is higher) would it be faster, slower orthe same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Faster</simple><quiz>If the same rocket was launched from the moon (where gravity is lower) would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a lighter material was used for the rocket body would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a you push a small object with some force, and then push a larger object with the same force, will the larger object go faster, slower or the same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Same speed</simple><quiz>If a rocket runs out of fuel in space, but it is moving foward, in 1000 years, will it be travelling faster, slower or at the same speed?</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Magnets" topics="7" level="5" index="67" inq="Magnets are used everyday in our lives, can you list some examples where we use magnets, that you havn't thought of before? (Don't be afraid to google for answers)" score="0"><model><simple>Magnets</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about magents, and magnetic fields</advanced></model><model><simple>Magnetism</simple><advanced>A magnet is a very special metal. When a magnet goes near a special kind of metal or other magnets, and the poles (sides) touching are opposite, it will pull, or attract the other metal or magnet closer. 
          Also, if the two poles are the same, the two magnets will push away, or repel, from each other. This is called magnetism. </advanced><advanced>Magnets can make some other metals into magnets when they are rubbed together.</advanced></model><model><simple>Soft magnets</simple><advanced>Soft magnets (or impermanent magnets) are often used in electromagnets. These enhance (often hundreds or thousands of times) the magnetic field of a wire that carries an electrical current and is wrapped around the magnet. </advanced><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Permanent magnets</simple><advanced>Permanent magnets have ferromagnetism. They occur naturally in some rocks, particularly lodestone, but are now commonly manufactured. </advanced><advanced>Magnets are only attracted to special metals. Iron, cobalt and nickel are magnetic. Metals that have iron in them attract magnets well. </advanced><advanced>Metals like brass, copper, zinc and aluminum are not attracted to magnets. Non-magnetic materials such as wood and glass are not attracted to magnets as they do not have magnetic materials in them.</advanced></model></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Classification" topics="8" level="5" index="68" inq="Can you think of another name to remember the levels in Linnaeus's system? Write them below!" score="0"><model><simple>Classifcation</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the history of taxonomy, and how we calssify all living things</advanced><advanced>Back in the 18th century, a Swedish man named Carolus Linnaeus thought it was important to organize living things, and he developed a system to do just that. </advanced><advanced>His system first only contained plants, however, he quickly expanded it to include all living organisms. We still use the essence of his system today. Scientists are constantly refining the system based on new knowledge. </advanced><advanced>Putting animals in order like this is called taxonomy. The taxonomists — people who name animals — use a book called the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, or ICZN, to tell them the rules for classifying animals.</advanced></model><model><simple>Linnaeus’s system</simple><advanced> His system has seven levels: Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, and Species</advanced><advanced>Every animal on the planet, down to the most microscopic creature you can imagine, can be classified according to this system.</advanced><advanced>An easy way to remember the order is to use the memonic: King Phillip, come out, for goodness’ sake!</advanced><quiz>This name of the system with which we organize living things</quiz></model><model><simple>Kingdom</simple><advanced>Generally, scientists agree there are six kingdoms. The animal kingdom (called Kingdom Animalia) is just one of those. </advanced><advanced>The others are Achaebacteria, Eubacteria, Protists, Fungi and Plants.</advanced><advanced>Originally, Linnaeus only identified two kingdoms: plant and animal. Some scientists think that viruses should have their own kingdom, but currently they are not included under this system.</advanced><advanced>Some animals found in the Animal kingdom are shown below</advanced><quiz>There are six of these</quiz><quiz>This is the first level of Linnaeus's sytem</quiz><quiz>Achaebacteria, protists, Fungi and Plants are all examples of this level</quiz></model><model><simple>Phylum</simple><advanced>Within the animal kingdom, the animals are divided into more than 30 phyla (which is the plural of “phylum”). </advanced><advanced>Some of the better known phyla are Phylum Chordata and Phylum Arthropoda. Phylum Chordata is the one humans and all animals with backbones are in.</advanced><advanced>Phylum Arthropoda contains insects, spiders and other animals with segmented bodies, like shrimp.  Arthropods have their skeletons on the outside of their bodies (think of the hard shell of a lobster) and other characteristics in common. </advanced><advanced>Some animals in the Phylum Chordata are shown below</advanced><quiz>This is the second level in Linnaeus's system</quiz><quiz>There are 30 of these in the animal kingdom</quiz></model><model><simple>Class</simple><advanced>The third level of classification is class. For example, Phylum Chordata has classes in it like birds, mammals (Mammalia) and reptiles.</advanced><advanced>Some animals in the Mammalia class are shown below</advanced><quiz>This is the third level of Linnaeus's system</quiz><quiz>Birds, mammals, and reptiles are examples of this level</quiz></model><model><simple>Order</simple><advanced>The next level, or rank, is order. Orders are smaller groups within the different classes.</advanced><advanced>Different orders include Lepidoptera and Carnivora. Lepidoptera is the order of moths and butterflies. Carnivora is the order within Mammalia that has the most diversity in animal size.</advanced><advanced>Some animals in the Carnivora order are shown below</advanced><quiz>This is the fourth level in Linnaeus's system</quiz><quiz>Lepidoptera, and Carnivora are examples of this level</quiz></model><model><simple>Family</simple><advanced>The fifth rank of classification is family. </advanced><advanced>Some animals in the Canidae family are shown below</advanced><quiz>This is the fifth level in Linnaeus's system</quiz></model><model><simple>Genus</simple><advanced>Genus the second-to-last rank, and a genus may have only one or two animals in it. If animals are in the same genus, they are really closely related. </advanced><advanced> In fact, you may not be able to tell them apart just by looking at them! When we write the name of the genus, we capitalize it and italicize it.</advanced><advanced>For example, the genus of dogs (and wolves, too!) is Canis.</advanced><quiz>This is the sixth level in Linnaeus's system</quiz><quiz>If animals are in this level together they are very closly related</quiz></model><model><simple>Species</simple><advanced>If animals can breed together successfully, they are a species. When an animal is called by its scientific name, then that means it is being identified by its genus and species. </advanced><advanced> We use a lowercase letter and italics for the species. </advanced><advanced>For example, the scientific name of dogs is Canis familiaris; however, the scientific name of wolves is Canis lupus.</advanced><quiz>This is the last level of Linnaeus's system</quiz><quiz>Animals are concidered together on this level if they can successfully breed together</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Scientific Names" topics="9" level="5" index="69" inq="Can you find some latin words that look very similar to the one we use in English? Can you explain why they are so similar?" score="0"><model><simple>Scientific Names</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about common scientific names </advanced></model><model><simple>Modern Humans</simple><advanced>Homo sapiens</advanced><quiz>Homo sapiens</quiz></model><model><simple>African elephant</simple><advanced>Loxodonta africana</advanced><quiz>Loxodonta africana</quiz></model><model><simple>Black rat</simple><advanced>Rattus rattus</advanced><quiz>Rattus rattus</quiz></model><model><simple>Cat</simple><advanced>Felis domesticus</advanced><quiz>Felis domesticus</quiz></model><model><simple>Dog</simple><advanced>Canis lupus familiaris</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus familiaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Horse</simple><advanced>Equus caballus</advanced><quiz>Equus caballus</quiz></model><model><simple>Lion</simple><advanced>Panthera leo</advanced><quiz>Panthera leo</quiz></model><model><simple>Wolf</simple><advanced>Canis lupus</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus</quiz></model><model><simple>Apple</simple><advanced>Malus pumila</advanced><quiz>Malus pumila</quiz></model><model><simple>Carrot</simple><advanced>Daucas carota</advanced><quiz>Daucas carota</quiz></model><model><simple>Lemon</simple><advanced>Citrus limonium</advanced><quiz>Citrus limonium</quiz></model><model><simple>Lettuce</simple><advanced>Lactuca sativa</advanced><quiz>Lactuca sativa</quiz></model><model><simple>Potato</simple><advanced>Solanum tubersum</advanced><quiz>Solanum tubersum</quiz></model><model><simple>Watermelon</simple><advanced>Citrullus vulgaris</advanced><quiz>Citrullus vulgaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Wheat</simple><advanced>Triticum aestivum</advanced><quiz>Triticum aestivum</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Animals" topics="10" level="5" index="70" inq="Can you think of some other animals that change over the course of their lives? Write them below!" score="10"><model><simple>Animal Life Cycles</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about some common animal life cycles, and how many animals change over the course of their lives</advanced></model><model><simple>Chickens</simple><advanced>A chicken is a kind of domesticated bird. It is raised widely for its meat and eggs. </advanced><advanced>There are 24 billion chickens worldwide. They are usually kept by humans as livestock, which means it is kept for its meat and eggs.</advanced><advanced>A male chicken is called a rooster or a cock (short for cockerel). A female chicken is called a hen. </advanced><quiz>These animals are domesticated birds, kept for their meat and eggs</quiz><quiz>There are about 24 billion of these kept by humans worldwide</quiz></model><model><simple>Chick</simple><advanced>Hens fiercely guard their chicks, and brood them when necessary to keep them warm, at first often returning to the nest at night. She leads them to food and water and will call them toward edible items, but seldom feeds them directly. She continues to care for them until they are several weeks old.</advanced><quiz>After hatching, this is what Chickens become</quiz></model><model><simple>Chicken Egg</simple><advanced>Fertile chicken eggs hatch at the end of the incubation period, about 21 days.</advanced><advanced>Development of the chick starts only when incubation begins, so all chicks hatch within a day or two of each other, despite perhaps being laid over a period of two weeks or so. </advanced><quiz>This is how chickens start their lives</quiz><quiz>These eggs hatch in about 21 days</quiz></model><model><simple>Beetles</simple><advanced>Beetles, the order Coleoptera, are the largest group of insects. There are 350,000 different species of beetles which have been named: about 40% of all known insects. </advanced><advanced>In common with other insects, there are three main parts to a beetle's body: the head, the thorax (the middle part), and the abdomen (the back part).</advanced><quiz>There are over 350,000 different types of these</quiz><quiz>Like other insects, these animals have three main parts, head, thorax and abdomen</quiz></model><model><simple>Beetle Pupa</simple><advanced>When the pupa opens, an adult beetle, sometimes called an imago, comes out. This way of growing up is called complete metamorphosis.</advanced><quiz>When this opens, and adult beetle, sometimes called an imago, comes out</quiz></model><model><simple>Beetle Instar</simple><advanced>A larva comes out when an egg hatches. Most beetle larvae do not look like adult beetles.</advanced><advanced> Beetles eat the most when they are larvae. A beetle larva eats and grows larger until it changes and becomes a pupa.</advanced><quiz>This is what hatches out of a beetle egg</quiz><quiz>Beetles eat most in this stage of their lives</quiz><quiz>This eats and grows until it becomes a pupa</quiz></model><model><simple>Beetle Egg</simple><advanced>Beetles start out as eggs that a female beetle lays. Some beetles can lay thousands of eggs during their lives.</advanced><quiz>Sometimes thousands of these can be laid at once</quiz></model><model><simple>Dragonflys</simple><advanced>Dragonflies are flying insects of the order Odonata. There are about 5,300 species of dragonfly. </advanced><advanced>Dragonflies have large compound eyes, which is their main sense organ. They have four strong transparent wings, and a long body. Even though dragonflies have six legs (like any other insect), they cannot walk.</advanced><advanced>Dragonflies are usually found around lakes, ponds, streams and wetlands. They are predators which eat mosquitoes, and other small insects such as flies, bees, ants, and butterflies.</advanced><advanced>Dragonflies have been around for 300 million years</advanced><quiz>There are about 5,300 different species of this animal</quiz><quiz>These animals are preditors, and eat mosquitoes and other small instects</quiz><quiz>These animals have existed for over 300 million years</quiz></model><model><simple>Larvae</simple><advanced>Dragonfly larvae, known as 'nymphs', are aquatic. While in the nymph stage they eat mosquito larvae and other things.</advanced><advanced>The larval stage of large dragonflies may last as long as five years. </advanced><advanced>Most of a dragonfly's life is spent in the nymph form, beneath the water's surface. It is quite active.</advanced><advanced> It can extend its jaws in front of its mouth to catch prey. Tiny vertebrates such as tadpoles and fish are part of its diet. Some nymphs even hunt on land. </advanced><advanced>They draw water in and out of their rectum. They can move fast by squirting water out of the anus. They also have gills in their rectum.</advanced><quiz>These animals, also known as 'nymphs' are aquatic</quiz><quiz>Most of the dragonflies life is spent in this stage</quiz></model><model><simple>Dragonfly Egg</simple><advanced>Female dragonflies lay eggs in or near water, often on plants. When laying eggs, some species go under the water to lay their eggs on a good surface</advanced><quiz>These eggs are laid near water, often on plants</quiz></model><model><simple>Buterflys</simple><advanced>A butterfly is a usually day-flying insect of the order Lepidoptera. They are grouped together in the suborder Rhopalocera. Butterflies are closely related to moths, from which they evolved.</advanced><advanced>The other notable features of butterflies are their extraordinary range of colours and patterns, and their wings.</advanced><advanced>Like moths, butterflies have four wings covered with tiny scales. When a butterfly is not flying, its wings are usually folded over its back. The wings are patterned and are often brightly coloured. </advanced><quiz>These animals evolved from moths</quiz><quiz>These animals are notible for their wings</quiz></model><model><simple>Buterfly Pupa</simple><advanced>The pupa (plural, pupae) is formed after the last molt. </advanced><advanced>During this stage, the digestive tract is emptied. The caterpillar sheds its skin. The pupa is now exposed. The caterpillar's tissues are broken down and rebuilt into the butterfly's tissues.</advanced><advanced>There are many tiny holes on the pupa. They allow respiratory gases to move in and out of the pupa.</advanced><advanced>Most butterfly pupae do not have cocoons to protect themselves. Instead, the pupae have brown or green colors to camouflage themselves among leaves and branches. Pupae that do not have cocoons are called chrysalids or chrysalises.</advanced><quiz>This is formed after the last molt of a butterfly</quiz><quiz>During this stage of a butterflys life, its tissues are borken down, then rebuilt</quiz><quiz>Most butterflys use colors, or cacoons to camouflage themselves during this stage</quiz></model><model><simple>Caterpillar</simple><advanced>Butterfly caterpillars can vary in size, color, and shape. They may have spines, bristles, or soft body extensions. All caterpillars have 13 body segments. </advanced><advanced>A caterpillar's skin does not grow. As the caterpillar grows inside its skin, the skin becomes too tight. In order for the caterpillar to grow bigger, it sheds </advanced><advanced> A caterpillar will molt four to five times before turning into a pupa. Each part between molts is called an instar.</advanced><quiz>This stage of the butterflys life is spent eating and molting mutliple times</quiz></model><model><simple>Buterfly Eggs</simple><advanced>A female butterfly will lay her eggs on or near the food plant of the caterpillar (the food plant is the plant that the caterpillar feeds on).</advanced><advanced> The female will choose a place to lay her eggs using smell, taste, touch, and sight. Most species will lay just one egg on the food plant. Others will lay groups of five to over 100 eggs on the food plant. </advanced><quiz>Often, only one of these eggs are laid on a food plant.</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Animal Cell" topics="14" level="5" index="71" inq="How does smoking effect the cells in the lungs? Do some research and summarize it below!" score="0"><model><simple>Nucleus</simple><advanced>The nucleus is small and round, and it works as the cell's control center. It contains chromosomes which house the DNA. The human body contains billions of cells, most of which have a nucleus.  </advanced><advanced>Inside the nucleus there are no membrane-bound sub-compartments. Its contents are not uniform, and a number of sub-nuclear bodies exist, made up of unique proteins, RNA molecules, and particular parts of the chromosomes.</advanced><advanced>The nucleus is surrounded by a nuclear membrane. Large molecules cannot get through the double-layer nuclear membrane: it is impermeable to them. However, nuclear pores exist. They control the movement of molecules across the membrane. </advanced><quiz>This contains the cells DNA</quiz><quiz>This organelle is small and round, and contains chromosones </quiz><quiz>This organelle has a membrane, which larger molecules cannot cross</quiz></model><model><simple>Ribosomes</simple><advanced>Ribosomes are important cell organelles. A ribosome is a large complex of RNA and protein.</advanced><advanced>It does RNA translation, building proteins from amino acids using messenger RNA as a template. Ribosomes are found in all living cells,</advanced><advanced>The job of the ribosome is to make new proteins. It does this by moving along a strand of RNA and building a protein based on the code it reads. Making a protein this way is called translation. Ribosomes are usually found in the rough endoplasmic reticulum, but can also be found throughout the cytoplasm.</advanced><quiz>This organelle is found in every cell, and is responsible for making protiens</quiz><quiz>This organelle is mainly found in the rough endoplasmic reticulum, but can be found in the cytoplasm as well</quiz><quiz>This organelle translates RNA to create new protiens</quiz></model><model><simple>Smooth Endoplasmic Reticulum</simple><advanced>Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is a cellular organelle. It is the transport network for molecules going to specific places, as compared to molecules that float freely in the cytoplasm.</advanced><advanced>Among its functions is the production of proteins and steroids, the maintenance of plasma membranes, and a pathway for molecules to move along.</advanced><advanced>It contains enzymes, proteins and lipids</advanced><quiz>This organelle contains enzymes, protiens and lipids</quiz><quiz>This organelle serves as a transport network</quiz><quiz>This organelle is responsible for the production of proteins, steroids and the maintenance of plasma membranes</quiz></model><model><simple>Rought Endoplasmic Reticulum</simple><advanced>Rough endoplasmic reticulum (rER), so called because it is studded with ribosomes, and secretes proteins into the cytoplasm.</advanced><advanced>Ribosomes are the location of protein synthesis, or where proteins used in the cell are put together</advanced><quiz>This organelle is covered in ribosomes</quiz><quiz>This organelle secretes proteins into the cytoplasm</quiz></model><model><simple>Lysosome</simple><advanced>A lysosome is a cell organelle. They are like spheres. They have hydrolytic enzymes which can break down almost all kinds of biomolecules, including proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, lipids, and cellular debris</advanced><advanced>Lysosomes work like the digestive system to break down, or digest, proteins, acids, carbohydrates, dead organelles, and other unwanted materials. They break up larger molecules into smaller molecules. Those smaller molecules can then be used again as building blocks for other large molecules.</advanced>       
      //    <advanced>Lysosomes are the proteins or carbohydrates released from the Golgi body</advanced>
     //     <advanced>Lysosomes connect to the cell membrane and releases their contents from inside their sac to outside of the cell.</advanced>
      //    <quiz>It releases its contents to outside the cell</quiz><quiz>These organelles are shaped like sphere's, and contain enzymes that break down most kinds of biomolecules</quiz><quiz>Thes organelles recycle larger molecules to be reused</quiz><quiz>This organlles are similar to a digestive system, and digest proteins, acids, carbohydrates and dead or unwanted materials</quiz></model><model><simple>Golgi Body</simple><advanced>The Golgi complex, also known as the Golgi apparatus or simply the Golgi, is a cytoplasmic organelle.</advanced><advanced>The main function of the Golgi apparatus is to process and package macromolecules, such as proteins and lipids. They come to the Golgi after being built, and before they go to their destination.</advanced><advanced>The Golgi complex inspects them for flaws and discards extra material added during their manufacture, wraps them up and then targets them for packaging. </advanced><advanced>The Golgi releases special enzymes called lysosomes, which clean off any extra amino acids. When the package is ready, it is pinched off the Golgi and released into the cytoplasm.</advanced>
          
       //   <advanced>The golgi body is a sac-like body that packages proteins and carbohydrates into membrane-covered sacs for export from the cell</advanced><quiz>This organelle processes and packages macromolecules</quiz><quiz>This organelle inspects macromolecules for flaws, before packaging them and sending them to their targets</quiz><quiz>This organelle releases lysosomes</quiz></model><model><simple>Mitochondrion</simple><advanced>The mitochondria are the power houses of the cell. They make most of the cell's supply of adenosine triphosphate (ATP), a molecule that cells use as a source of energy. </advanced><advanced>Their main job is this energy conversion. They oxidise glucose to provide energy for the cell. The process makes ATP, and is called cellular respiration.</advanced><advanced>In addition to supplying cellular energy, mitochondria are involved in a range of other processes, such as signalling, cellular differentiation, cell death, as well as the control of the cell division cycle and cell growth.</advanced><advanced>It is thought that mitochondria were once independent bacteria, and became part of the eukaryotic cells by being engulfed, a process called endosymbiosis.</advanced><quiz>This organelle supplies the cell with energy</quiz><quiz>This organelle supplies the cell with a chemical called ATP</quiz><quiz>This organelle is thought to have once been a seperate bacteria</quiz></model><model><simple>Vacuoles</simple><advanced>Vacuoles are organelles that are filled with fluid and remove waste products from the cell</advanced><advanced>Vacuoles are also digestive and help break down food material within the cell.</advanced><quiz>It removes waste from the cell</quiz></model><model><simple>Centrosome</simple><advanced>In cell biology, the centrosome is an organelle that is the main place where cell microtubules are organized.</advanced><advanced> They occur only in animal cells. Also, it regulates the cell division cycle, the stages which lead up to cell division.</advanced><advanced>A centrosome is composed of two centrioles at right angles to each another. They are surrounded by a shapeless mass of protein.</advanced><quiz>This organelle is the place where microtubles get organized</quiz><quiz>This organelle is composed of two centroiles at right angles to each other</quiz></model><model><simple>Microtubles</simple><advanced>Microtubules are found in biological cells as a part of the cytoskeleton. </advanced><advanced>They are hollow tubes whose walls consist of 13 columns of tubulin molecules. Its main functions are to maintain a cell's shape, cell motility, chromosome movement in cell division, and organelle movement. </advanced><advanced>They look like hollow noodles which transmit signals to our nerves</advanced><quiz>These are responsible for maintaining a cells shape, and chromosone movment</quiz><quiz>These organelles are hollow tubes, and look like hollow noodles</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Plant Cell" topics="15" level="5" index="72" inq="Can you explain the difference and similarities between animal and plant cells?" score="0"><model><simple>Nucleus</simple><advanced>The nucleus is small and round, and it works as the cell's control center. It contains chromosomes which house the DNA. The human body contains billions of cells, most of which have a nucleus.  </advanced><advanced>Inside the nucleus there are no membrane-bound sub-compartments. Its contents are not uniform, and a number of sub-nuclear bodies exist, made up of unique proteins, RNA molecules, and particular parts of the chromosomes.</advanced><advanced>The nucleus is surrounded by a nuclear membrane. Large molecules cannot get through the double-layer nuclear membrane: it is impermeable to them. However, nuclear pores exist. They control the movement of molecules across the membrane. </advanced><quiz>This contains the cells DNA</quiz><quiz>This organelle is small and round, and contains chromosones </quiz><quiz>This organelle has a membrane, which larger molecules cannot cross</quiz></model><model><simple>Ribosomes</simple><advanced>Ribosomes are important cell organelles. A ribosome is a large complex of RNA and protein.</advanced><advanced>It does RNA translation, building proteins from amino acids using messenger RNA as a template. Ribosomes are found in all living cells,</advanced><advanced>The job of the ribosome is to make new proteins. It does this by moving along a strand of RNA and building a protein based on the code it reads. Making a protein this way is called translation. Ribosomes are usually found in the rough endoplasmic reticulum, but can also be found throughout the cytoplasm.</advanced><quiz>This organelle is found in every cell, and is responsible for making protiens</quiz><quiz>This organelle is mainly found in the rough endoplasmic reticulum, but can be found in the cytoplasm as well</quiz><quiz>This organelle translates RNA to create new protiens</quiz></model><model><simple>Smooth Endoplasmic Reticulum</simple><advanced>Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is a cellular organelle. It is the transport network for molecules going to specific places, as compared to molecules that float freely in the cytoplasm.</advanced><advanced>Among its functions is the production of proteins and steroids, the maintenance of plasma membranes, and a pathway for molecules to move along.</advanced><advanced>It contains enzymes, proteins and lipids</advanced><quiz>This organelle contains enzymes, protiens and lipids</quiz><quiz>This organelle serves as a transport network</quiz><quiz>This organelle is responsible for the production of proteins, steroids and the maintenance of plasma membranes</quiz></model><model><simple>Rought Endoplasmic Reticulum</simple><advanced>Rough endoplasmic reticulum (rER), so called because it is studded with ribosomes, and secretes proteins into the cytoplasm.</advanced><advanced>Ribosomes are the location of protein synthesis, or where proteins used in the cell are put together</advanced><quiz>This organelle is covered in ribosomes</quiz><quiz>This organelle secretes proteins into the cytoplasm</quiz></model><model><simple>Lysosome</simple><advanced>A lysosome is a cell organelle. They are like spheres. They have hydrolytic enzymes which can break down almost all kinds of biomolecules, including proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, lipids, and cellular debris</advanced><advanced>Lysosomes work like the digestive system to break down, or digest, proteins, acids, carbohydrates, dead organelles, and other unwanted materials. They break up larger molecules into smaller molecules. Those smaller molecules can then be used again as building blocks for other large molecules.</advanced>
          //    <advanced>Lysosomes are the proteins or carbohydrates released from the Golgi body</advanced>
          //     <advanced>Lysosomes connect to the cell membrane and releases their contents from inside their sac to outside of the cell.</advanced>
          //    <quiz>It releases its contents to outside the cell</quiz><quiz>These organelles are shaped like sphere's, and contain enzymes that break down most kinds of biomolecules</quiz><quiz>Thes organelles recycle larger molecules to be reused</quiz><quiz>This organlles are similar to a digestive system, and digest proteins, acids, carbohydrates and dead or unwanted materials</quiz></model><model><simple>Golgi Body</simple><advanced>The Golgi complex, also known as the Golgi apparatus or simply the Golgi, is a cytoplasmic organelle.</advanced><advanced>The main function of the Golgi apparatus is to process and package macromolecules, such as proteins and lipids. They come to the Golgi after being built, and before they go to their destination.</advanced><advanced>The Golgi complex inspects them for flaws and discards extra material added during their manufacture, wraps them up and then targets them for packaging. </advanced><advanced>The Golgi releases special enzymes called lysosomes, which clean off any extra amino acids. When the package is ready, it is pinched off the Golgi and released into the cytoplasm.</advanced>

          //   <advanced>The golgi body is a sac-like body that packages proteins and carbohydrates into membrane-covered sacs for export from the cell</advanced><quiz>This organelle processes and packages macromolecules</quiz><quiz>This organelle inspects macromolecules for flaws, before packaging them and sending them to their targets</quiz><quiz>This organelle releases lysosomes</quiz></model><model><simple>Mitochondrion</simple><advanced>The mitochondria are the power houses of the cell. They make most of the cell's supply of adenosine triphosphate (ATP), a molecule that cells use as a source of energy. </advanced><advanced>Their main job is this energy conversion. They oxidise glucose to provide energy for the cell. The process makes ATP, and is called cellular respiration.</advanced><advanced>In addition to supplying cellular energy, mitochondria are involved in a range of other processes, such as signalling, cellular differentiation, cell death, as well as the control of the cell division cycle and cell growth.</advanced><advanced>It is thought that mitochondria were once independent bacteria, and became part of the eukaryotic cells by being engulfed, a process called endosymbiosis.</advanced><quiz>This organelle supplies the cell with energy</quiz><quiz>This organelle supplies the cell with a chemical called ATP</quiz><quiz>This organelle is thought to have once been a seperate bacteria</quiz></model><model><simple>Plastids</simple><advanced>There are three main types of plastids, myloplasts, chloroplasts, and chromoplasts</advanced><advanced>Chloroplasts generate energy throught photosynthesis, which is then used to manufacture glucose and starch from carbon dioxide and water.</advanced><advanced>Chromoplasts do not contain chlorophyll but they contain carotenoids. Carotenoids are pigments which give plants their red and yellow colors</advanced><quiz>It generates sugar in a process called photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Vacuoles</simple><advanced> Vacuoles are organelles which store different types of substances and help the cell grow. They can contain sugars, ions, or simply, water.</advanced><advanced>In plant cells, vacuoles help keep the cell rigid.</advanced><quiz>It stores different substances to help the cell grow</quiz></model><model><simple>Peroxisome</simple><advanced>peroxisomes are similar to lysosomes. They are small vesicles found around the cell, adn they have a single membrane that contains digestive enzymes for breaking down toxic materials in the cell.</advanced><advanced>They differ from lysosomes in the type of enzyme they hold. Peroxisomes hold on to enzymes that require oxygen (oxidative enzymes). Lysosomes have enzymes that work in oxygen-poor areas and lower pH.</advanced><advanced>They are very well known for digesting fatty acids. They also play a part in the way organisms digest alcohol (ethanol).</advanced><quiz>These organelles hold on to enzymes that require oxygen</quiz></model><model><simple>Plasmodesma </simple><advanced>Plasmodesma is a microscopic channel across the cell wall of a plant cell. It allows transport and communication between neighbouring cells.</advanced><advanced>Unlike animal cells, every plant cell is surrounded by a polysaccharide cell wall.</advanced><quiz>These allow for communication and transportion of materials between cells</quiz></model><model><simple>Cell Membrane</simple><advanced>The Cell membrane is the barrier that determines what is inside and what is outside the cell</advanced><advanced>The membrane is made of proteins and can change forms as vacuoles and lysosomes combine to create a new membrane to expel wastes from the cell</advanced><quiz>This is the barrier of the cell</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Ecosystems" topics="41" level="5" index="73" inq="What type of ecosystem do you live in, which would be your favorite ecosystem to live in and why?" score="0"><model><simple>Ecosystems</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn to identify and classify the major ecosystems on our planet</advanced></model><model><simple>Forest Ecosystems</simple><advanced>Forest ecosystems are classified according to their climate type as tropical, temperate or boreal.</advanced><advanced> In the tropics, rainforest ecosystems contain more diverse flora and fauna than ecosystems in any other region on earth.</advanced><advanced> In temperate zones, forest ecosystems may be deciduous, coniferous or oftentimes a mixture of both, in which some trees shed their leaves each fall, while others remain evergreen year-round.</advanced><advanced>In the far north, just south of the Arctic, boreal forests – also known as taiga – feature abundant coniferous trees.</advanced><quiz>This type of ecoystem can either be tropical, temperate or boreal</quiz><quiz>Rainforests are apart of this ecosystem</quiz></model><model><simple>Grassland Ecosystems</simple><advanced>Different types of grassland ecosystems can be found in prairies, savannas and steppes.</advanced><advanced>Grassland ecosystems are typically found in tropical or temperate regions, although they can exist in colder areas as well, as is the case with the well-known Siberian steppe. </advanced><advanced>Trees are sparse or nonexistent, but flowers may be interspersed with the grasses. Grasslands provide an ideal environment for grazing animals.</advanced><quiz>This type of ecosystem can be found in prairies, savannas and steppes</quiz><quiz>This type of ecosystem is ideal for grazing animals</quiz></model><model><simple>Desert Ecosystems</simple><advanced>The common defining feature among desert ecosystems is low precipitation, generally less than 25 centimeters, or 10 inches, per year.</advanced><advanced>Not all deserts are hot – desert ecosystems can exist from the tropics to the arctic, but regardless of latitude, deserts are often windy. </advanced><advanced> Vegetation is sparse or nonexistent, and any animal species, such as insects, reptiles and birds, must be highly adapted to the dry conditions.</advanced><quiz>This type of ecosystem has very low precipitation</quiz></model><model><simple>Tundra Ecosystems</simple><advanced>In the snow-covered, windswept, treeless tundra, the soil may be frozen year-round, a condition known as permafrost. </advanced><advanced>During the brief spring and summer, snows melt, producing shallow ponds which attract migrating waterfowl.</advanced><advanced>The term “tundra” most commonly denotes polar areas, but at lower latitudes, tundra-like communities known as alpine tundra may be found at high elevations.</advanced><quiz>This type of ecosystem can have a condition known as permafrost</quiz><quiz>This type of ecosystem is commonly found in polar areas</quiz></model><model><simple>Freshwater Ecosystems</simple><advanced>Freshwater ecosystems can be found in streams, rivers, springs, ponds, lakes, bogs and freshwater swamps. </advanced><advanced>They are subdivided into two classes: those in which the water is nearly stationary, such as ponds, and those in which the water flows, such as creeks. </advanced><advanced> Freshwater ecosystems are home to more than just fish: algae, plankton, insects, amphibians and underwater plants also inhabit them.</advanced><quiz>This type of ecosystem can be divied into two classes, flowing and stationary water</quiz><quiz>This type of ecosystem is home to fish, algea, plankton, and insects amoung others</quiz></model><model><simple>Marine Ecosystems</simple><advanced>Marine ecosystems differ from freshwater ecosystems in that they contain saltwater, which usually supports different types of species than does freshwater. </advanced><advanced> Marine ecosystems are the most abundant types of ecosystems in the word. They encompass not only the ocean floor and surface but also tidal zones, estuaries, salt marshes and saltwater swamps, mangroves and coral reefs.</advanced><quiz>This is the most abundant type of ecosystem in the world</quiz><quiz>This ecosystem contains tidal zones, salt marshes and saltwater swamps</quiz></model></lesson> //this one is identifiying
      <lesson name="Ecology" topics="16" level="5" index="74" inq="Can you explain why it is important to understand Earth and natrure? Write your answers below!" score="0"><model><simple>Ecology</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about ecology, and its basic termonology</advanced><advanced>Ecology is the science which studies the biota, the environment, and their interactions. It comes from the Greek oikos = house; logos = study.</advanced><advanced>Ecology is the study of ecosystems. Ecosystems describe the web or network of relations among organisms at different scales of organization.</advanced><advanced>ecologists research everything from tiny bacteria in nutrient recycling to the effects of tropical rain forests on the Earth's atmosphere. </advanced></model><model><simple>Biodiversity</simple><advanced>Biodiversity (an abbreviation of "biological diversity") describes the diversity of life from genes to ecosystems and spans every level of biological organization.</advanced><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple></simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple></simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple></simple><advanced></advanced></model></lesson> //this one is general (get rid of this)
      <lesson name="Conservation and natural resources" topics="17" level="5" index="75" score="0"></lesson> //recycling
      <lesson name="Energy Sources" topics="42" level="5" index="76" inq="Which energy source is the best in your opinion? Explain why!" score="0"><model><simple>Nuclear power</simple><advanced>Nuclear power is the controlled use of nuclear energy. Nuclear energy is energy in uranium that can be released by nuclear reactions in a machine called a nuclear reactor. This energy is made into electricity, which then can be used to power machines and heat homes.</advanced><advancd>14% of the world's electricity came from nuclear power. Nuclear power plants also make radioactive waste that could be harmful if it is not stored properly. Nuclеar power plants produce less radioactive material than a coal fired power station</advancd><advanced>Nuclear power plants opperate on a process known as fission, which takes a larger molecule and breaks it into smaller pieces, releasing energy in the process</advanced><advanced>The sun uses a process known as nuclear fussion, which joins two smaller molecules together to form a larger one, releasing a huge amount of heat. Researchers hope to use this form of energy in the future, as it is safer, more efficient, and greener that any current technology</advanced><quiz>It generates energy from radioactive materials</quiz><quiz>This power source operates on a process known as nuclear fission</quiz><quiz>This power source has caused many disasters, such as Chernobyl, or Three Mile Island</quiz></model><model><simple>Hyrdo power</simple><advanced>Hydroelectricity is electricity that is made by the movement of water. It is usually made with dams that block a river to make a reservoir or collect water that is pumped there.</advanced><advanced>When the water is "let go", the huge pressure behind the dam forces the water down pipes that lead to a turbine. This causes the turbine to turn, which turns a generator which makes electricity. </advanced><advaced>The way the electricity is produced does not harm the environment as much as fossil fuels like oil or coal do. Hydroelectricity is very powerful and safe, and produces no waste.</advaced><quiz>This form of power uses the flowing of water to generate electricity</quiz><quiz>This power source can cause flooding in some areas, and can damage the ecosystem</quiz></model><model><simple>Oil power</simple><advanced>Our main sources of energy today are fossil fuels. There are three main types of fossil fuels: coal, oil, and natural gas.</advanced><advanced>Coal is a solid material that is burned to create heat in homes, or used in power plants to produce electricity. Oil is a liquid fossil fuel, used to produce gasoline. Natural gas can be used for cooking, heating, or generating electricity.</advanced><advanced>All fossil fuels are nonrenewable resources. It took millions of years to form fossil fuels and we are currently using it up faster than it is being made.</advanced><advanced>Another challenge to using nonrenewable energy sources is that they can cause pollution. Burning fossil fuels releases chemicals into the air and water.</advanced><quiz>This is our main form of generating electricity currently, however it is harmful to the enviornment</quiz><quiz>This power source uses organic material that is millions of years old</quiz></model><model><simple>Wind power</simple><advanced>Wind energy is the energy from the bulk movement of air. Wind is caused by pressure differences in the atmosphere which are caused by uneven heating of the earth by the sun. </advanced><advanced>Air moves from areas of higher pressure to areas of lower pressure, which produces wind as a result.</advanced><advanced> Wind power is the fastest growing renewable energy source. It is also the most widely available renewable energy source in the world.</advanced><advanaced> The height of a turbine tower can be over 100 meters, and the blades can be over 100 meters in diameter. A wind turbine this large can produce several megawatts of electricity, which is enough for a small town</advanaced><advanced>Wind turbines are often found near oceans or plains, as the wind is stronger there</advanced><quiz>This is the fastest growing renewable energy source</quiz><quiz>This energy source uses the movment of air to create electricity</quiz><quiz>This energy source can be over 100 meters tall</quiz><quiz>This energy source is often found near oceans, or fields</quiz></model><model><simple>Solar power</simple><advanced>Solar energy is the energy that is in sunlight. Solar power plants convert sunlight into electricity, either directly using photovoltaics (PV), or indirectly using concentrated solar power (CSP).</advanced><advanced>Concentrated solar power systems use lenses or mirrors and tracking systems to focus a large area of sunlight into a small beam. Photovoltaics converts light into electric current using the photoelectric effect.</advanced><quiz>This form of energy uses the technology of photovoltaics, or concentrated solar power, to generate electricity</quiz><quiz>This form of energy can only produce electricity during the day</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Rocks and minerals" topics="18" level="5" index="77" inq="Can you identify all the rocks in your local park? What are the most common types of rocks you found?" score="0"><model><simple>Calcite</simple><advanced>Calcite is a common rock forming mineral</advanced><advanced>Calcite is found in all 3 types of rocks</advanced><advanced>It is used in all parts of our lives, from construction to pharmecutical industires</advanced><quiz>It is a common rock building mineral</quiz></model><model><simple>Sedimentary rock</simple><advanced>Sedimentary rocks are formed in layers over time often at the bottom of lakes and oceans </advanced><quiz>It is formed over time at the bottom of lakes</quiz></model><model><simple>Igneous rock</simple><advanced>The rock shown here is Gnaisse which is a common form of igneous rock</advanced><advanced>Igneous rocks are formed from volcanic activity, under high heat and pressure</advanced><quiz>It is formed from volcanic activity</quiz></model><model><simple>Limestone</simple><advanced>Limestone is a sedimentary rock</advanced><advanced>It is often composed of the skeletal fragments of marine organisms such as coral</advanced><quiz>It is often made of skeletal fragments of marine organisms</quiz></model><model><simple>Quartz</simple><advanced>Quartz is a mineral made of silicon and oxygen</advanced><advanced>It is the second most abundant material</advanced><quiz>It is made of silicon and oxygen</quiz></model><model><simple>Metamorphic rock</simple><advanced>A metamorphic rock is a type of rock which has been changed by extreme heat and pressure. Its name is from 'morph' (meaning form), and 'meta' (meaning change).</advanced><advanced>The original rock may be sedimentary rock, igneous rock or another older metamorphic rock.</advanced><advanced>for example marble is a metamorphic rock formed from limestone.</advanced><quiz>This type of rock has been changed from extreme heat and pressure</quiz></model></lesson> //ok, so here you need to have all the labels and information 
      <lesson name="Fossils" topics="19" level="5" index="78" inq="Can you explain how fossils become burried so deep in the ground?" score="0"><model section="1"><simple>Fossils</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about fossils, how they are formed, how they are found, and why they are important</advanced><advanced>A fossil is the remains or trace of an ancient living thing. Fossils of animals, plants or protists occur in sedimentary rock.</advanced><advanced>In a typical fossil, the body form is retained, but the original molecules that made up the body have been replaced by some inorganic material, such as calcium carbonate (CaCO3) or silica (SiO2). It has been mineralised or petrified (literally, turned into rock).</advanced><advanced>Some organisms fossilise well, others do not. The most common fossils are those left behind by organisms that produce hard materials.</advanced><advanced>The study of fossils by geologists and biologists is known as paleontology. If the study puts living things in their ecological context it is called paleobiology.</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Types of fossils</simple><advanced>Microscopic or very tiny fossils are called "microfossils"; while larger, macroscopic fossils — such as those of seashells and mammals — are called "macrofossils".</advanced><advanced>Although most fossils are formed from the hard parts of organisms, there are also indirect signs of prehistoric life. Examples such as a worm's trail or an animal's footprint are quite common. They are known as trace fossils. </advanced><advanced> Fossilized excrement, faeces or dung is known as a coprolite.</advanced><advanced> Chemical traces of prehistoric organisms is called a chemofossil.</advanced><advanced>Objects made by prehistoric people are called artifacts.</advanced></model><model><simple>Coelophysis</simple><advanced>Coelophysis is a small dinosaur that lived approximately 200 million years ago in the Late Triassic Period. </advanced><advanced>It is named it Coelophysis—which means “hollow form”–because this dinosaur had hollow bones.</advanced><advanced>This dinosaur was about 9 feet long, 3 feet high and weighed about 100 pounds at most. It’s hollow bone structure made it light and agile,</advanced><quiz>This dinosaur lived about 200 million years ago, and had hollow bones</quiz></model><model><simple>Giant ground sloth</simple><advanced>Giant ground sloths were large, lumbering beasts that lived in the Americas during the Ice Age. They were directly related to today's modern sloths. They were also distantly related to anteaters and armadillos.</advanced><advanced>By the end of the Great Ice Age, around 11,700 years ago, many believe that the giant ground sloths had become extinct. Some argue that they were around for many more thousands of years, though, surviving on islands in the Caribbean.</advanced><quiz>This animal lived during the Ice Age, and are related to todays sloths</quiz></model><model><simple>Mammoth</simple><advanced>Mammoths were hairy elephants of the genus Mammuthus. They lived in Europe until 4,500 years ago, and were adapted to cold climate. They were killed off by hunters and climate change.</advanced><advanced>Like their modern relatives, mammoths were quite large. The largest known species reached heights in the region of 4 m (13.1 ft) at the shoulder and weights of up to 8 tonnes (8.8 short tons), while exceptionally large males may have exceeded 12 tonnes (13.2 short tons). </advanced><advanced>Their diet was mainly grazing, these assumptions were based on mammoth feces and mammoth teeth, such as the molar shown here</advanced><advanced>European mammoths had a major diet of C3 carbon fixation plants. This was determined by examining the isotopic data from the European mammoth teeth.</advanced></model><model><simple>Short faced bear</simple><advanced>The short-faced bear or bulldog bear (Arctodus) is an extinct genus of bear endemic to North America during the Pleistocene era about 1.8 million years ago (mya) to 11,000 years ago. </advanced><advanced>At that time it may have been one of the largest mammals that lived on land and ate meat.</advanced><advanced>The short-faced bear lived in many parts of North America, ranging from Alaska to Mississippi. However, it lived mostly in southern areas, from northern Texas to New Jersey in the east; Aguascalientes, Mexico to the southwest; and with large concentrations in Florida.</advanced><advanced>The short face bear found was estimated to be largest was 957 kg (2,110 lb). When it was standing on its hind (back) legs, the bear was 8–10 feet (2.4–3.0 m) tall.</advanced><quiz>This animal lived during the Ice Age, and was the largest land carnivour at the time</quiz></model><model><simple>Spinosaurus</simple><advanced>Spinosaurus (which means 'spiny lizard') was a huge semi-aquatic dinosaur from the Cretaceous, 112 to 97 million years ago. It had paddle-like feet and nostrils on top of its crocodile-like head.</advanced><advanced>Estimates suggest that it was 12.6 to 18 metres (41 to 59 ft) in length and 7 to 20.9 tonnes (7.7 to 23.0 short tons) in weight. </advanced><advanced>It lived in what is now Sahara Desert, but which then was mangrove forests alongside shoreline conditions, tidal flats and channels.</advanced><advanced>Spinosaurus is known to have eaten fish. Evidence suggests that it lived both on land and in water like a modern crocodilian.</advanced><quiz>This dinosaur is related to todays crocodile</quiz></model><model><simple>Trilobite</simple><advanced>Trilobite (meaning "three lobed") are extinct arthropods. Their name is in reference to the three round parts, called lobes, across their heads</advanced><advanced>Trilobites appeared some 600 million years ago during the Cambrian period. They belonged to the phylum Arthropoda (joint-footed), a phylum which to this day represents the most successful (78%) of all animal life forms, including crabs, centipedes, spiders, shrimps and insects. </advanced><advanced>Trilobites are the earliest known animal to have vision. Some possessed eyes and some seem to have no eyes at all, while others had eyes made up of many parts that could see all around the animal. </advanced><advanced>Trilobites ranged in length from 1 millimetre (0.04 in) to 72 centimetres (28 in), with a typical size range of 3–10 cm (1.2–3.9 in). </advanced><quiz>These animals were one ofthe first to have eyes </quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Greenhouse gasses" topics="20" level="5" index="79" inq="What can people do to reduce the amount of greenhouse gasses?" score="0"><model><simple>Greenhouse gases</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the common greenhouse gasses, and the effect they have on our atmosphere and climate</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>The Greenhouse effect</simple><advanced>Greenhouse gases reflect radiation that the Earth emits, and stop it from being lost into space. This causes the Earth's temperature to be higher than it would be without greenhouse gases. The name for this is the "greenhouse effect."</advanced><quiz>This is the effect that causes radiation to be reflected back to Earth</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Greenhouse gasses</simple><advanced>Most greenhouse gases are natural - water vapor is the most common, and causes most of the greenhouse effect on Earth. Other greenhouse gases are carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide, chlorofluorocarbon and ozone.</advanced><advanced>Without greenhouse gases, the earth would be on average 33 degrees Celsius colder.</advanced><quiz>These are gasses that cause the greenhouse effect</quiz><quiz>Without these gasses the earth would be 33 degrees colder</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Water vapour</simple><advanced>Water vapour is the most abundant greenhouse gas in the atmosphere, both by weight and by volume </advanced><advanced>Water vapour will generally stay in the atmosphere for days (before precipitating out) while other greenhouse gases, such as carbon dioxide or methane, will stay in the atmosphere for a much longer period of time (ranging from years to centuries) thus contributing to warming for an extended period of time.</advanced><advanced>Increased water vapor content in the atmosphere is referred to as a feedback process. Warmer air is able to hold more moisture. As the climate warms, air temperatures rise, more evaporation from water sources and land occurs, thus increasing the atmospheric moisture content. </advanced><advanced>The water vapour feedback process is most likely responsible for a doubling of the greenhouse effect when compared to the addition of carbon dioxide on its own </advanced><quiz>This is the most abundant greenhouse gas</quiz><quiz>This greenhous gas causes a feedback loop that doubles the greenhouse effect</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Carbon dioxide</simple><advanced>Carbon dioxide is a natually occuring gas, that is relased from decaying and living organisms, as well as volcanoes</advanced><advanced>Carbon dioxide is also relased when burning fossil fuels such as coal or oil, and it is the most important contributer to man-made greenhouse gasses</advanced><quiz>This greenhouse gas is released by living and decaying organisms, as well as volcanoes</quiz><quiz>This greenhouse gas is the most important contributer of man-made greenhouse gasses</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Methane</simple><advanced>Methane is a normal gas released from wetlands, growing rise, raising cattle, using natural gas, and mining coal</advanced><advanced>However, methane traps alot of heat, and is concidered the second most important contributer to man-made greenhosue gasses</advanced><quiz>This greenhouse gas is realeased from wetlands, growing rice, and mining coal</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Nitrous oxide</simple><advanced>Nitrous oxide is a natural part of the nitrogen cycle, and is released from bacteria in the soil and ocean</advanced><advanced>However, it is also released by some factories, power plants, and fertilizers. This gas damages the protective ozone layer, and is extreamly powerful </advanced><quiz>This gas damages the protective ozone layer</quiz></model></lesson> //not one
      <lesson name="Water cycle" topics="21" level="5" index="80" inq="Can you explain how global warming can cause more rain in some areas?" score="0"><model><simple>Evaporation</simple><advanced>Energy from the sun causes water to evaporate from bodies of water</advanced><advanced>The main factors affecting evaporation are temperature, humidity, wind speed, and solar radiation.</advanced><advanced>The principal source of water vapour is the oceans, but evaporation also occurs in soils, snow, and ice.</advanced><advanced>Around 90 percent of the water vapor in the atmosphere got there through evaporation.</advanced><quiz>Throught this process water rises to forms clouds</quiz></model><model><simple>Condensation</simple><advanced>Condensation is the process of water vapour forming clouds</advanced><advanced>Water vapor gas condenses back into liquid water and ice, which you mainly see as clouds and then as rain and snow.</advanced><advanced>Condensation happens because of temperature changes.</advanced><quiz>This is the process during which water vapour forms clouds</quiz></model><model><simple>Percipitation</simple><advanced>Precipitation is when water falls from the atmosphere back to land.</advanced><advanced>Depending on the temperature and weather this could be rain, snow, sleet, or even hail.</advanced><quiz>This is how water returns from clouds to the ground level</quiz></model><model><simple>Transpiration</simple><advanced>Transpiration is when plants release water on to their leaves that then evaporates into vapor.</advanced><advanced>Around 10 percent of the water vapor in the atmosphere is estimated to come from transpiration.</advanced><quiz>This is the process during which plants release water that is evaporated</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Astronomy" topics="22" level="5" index="81" inq="What would be the best planet for humans to colonize? The second best?" score="0"><model><simple>Mercury</simple><advanced>Mercury is the smallest, and closest planet to the sun</advanced><advanced>It completes one full revolution around the sun in 88 days</advanced><advanced>Mercury has no atmosphere</advanced><quiz>It is the smallest planet in the solar system</quiz></model><model><simple>Venus</simple><advanced>Venus has a thick atmosphere, of carbon dioxide and sulfuric acid</advanced><advanced>The average temprature on Venus is over 900 degrees</advanced><advanced>Venus has over 100,000 active volcanos</advanced><quiz>It it has clouds made of acid</quiz></model><model><simple>Earth</simple><advanced>It is the only known planet with life</advanced><advanced>Earth's atmosphere is made up of about 80% nitrogen, and 20% oxygen</advanced><advanced>The surface of Earth is about 70% water</advanced><quiz>The surface of this planet is 70% water</quiz></model><model><simple>Mars</simple><advanced>The average temprature on Mars is -63 degrees Celcius</advanced><advanced>Mars is about half the size of Earth</advanced><advanced>Mars is red because it is coverd in a layer of iron oxide - rust</advanced><quiz>This planet is covered in a layer of iron oxide</quiz></model><model><simple>Jupiter</simple><advanced>Jupiter is the largest planet in the solar system</advanced><advanced>Jupiter is covered in clouds of hydrogen, helium and ammonium</advanced><advanced>Jupiter has over 50 moons, some of which are as large as planets</advanced><quiz>It is the largest planet in our solar system</quiz></model><model><simple>Saturn</simple><advanced>Saturn is made of mostly hydrogen and helium</advanced><advanced>Saturn has rings made of dust and ice</advanced><advanced>Saturn has over 52 moons</advanced><advanced>One year on Saturn is over 10,759 Earth days</advanced><quiz>This planet is famous for its rings</quiz></model><model><simple>Uranus</simple><advanced>Uranus is the 7th planet from the sun, and the thrid gas giant, after Jupiter and Saturn</advanced><advanced>Uranus has been tipped on its side, most likely by another planet</advanced><advanced>Uranuus has 27 moons named after characters from William Shakespeare</advanced><quiz>This planet has been tipped on its side</quiz></model><model><simple>Neptune</simple><advanced>Neptune is the farthest planet from the sun</advanced><advanced>Neptune has some of the fiersest storms in the solar system, with winds reaching over 1900 km/h</advanced><advanced>The average temprature on Neptune is -214 degrees Celsius</advanced><quiz>This is the farthest planet from the sun</quiz></model><model><simple>Pluto</simple><advanced>Pluto is a dwarf planet</advanced><advanced>It is mainly made of rock and ice</advanced><quiz>It is the nineth largest body orbiting the sun</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Chemical reactions" topics="26" level="5" index="84" inq="Can you think of some chemical reactions we use everyday?" score="0"><model><simple>Chemical reactions</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about some common chemical reactions, what they are, and how they work</advanced></model>
        //synthesis
        <model><simple>Creating water</simple><advanced>Water is the common name for dihydrogen monoxide or H2O. </advanced><advanced>In theory, it's easy to make water from hydrogen gas and oxygen gas. Mix the two gases together, add a spark or sufficient heat to provide the activation energy to start the reaction, and presto—instant water.</advanced><advanced>Merely mixing the two gases at room temperature, however, won't do anything, energy must be supplied to break the covalent bonds that hold H2 and O2 molecules together.</advanced><advanced>When the chemical bonds re-form to make water, additional energy is released, which propagates the reaction. The net reaction is highly exothermic, meaning a reaction that is accompanied by the release of heat.</advanced></model><model><simple>Photosynthesis</simple><advanced>Photosynthesis is the process by which plants and other things make food. It is a chemical process that uses sunlight to turn carbon dioxide into sugars the cell can use as energy.</advanced><advanced>Light energy from the sun is used to split water molecules (photolysis). The sunlight hits chloroplasts in the plant, causing an enzyme to break apart the water. Water, when broken, makes oxygen, hydrogen, and electrons.</advanced><advanced>Hydrogen, along with electrons energized by light, converts NADP into NADPH</advanced><advanced>Oxygen diffuses out of the plant as a waste product of photosynthesis</advanced></model>
        //to add
        <model><simple>Creating salt</simple><advanced>Sodium is a chemical element with the symbol Na and atomic number 11. It is a soft, silvery-white, highly reactive metal. Sodium is so soft that it can be easily cut with a knife.</advanced><advanced>Sodium is easily dissolved in water, sodium and chlorine are the most common dissolved elements by weight in the oceans.</advanced><advanced>Chlorine is a very irritating and greenish-yellow gas. It has a strong smell like bleach. It is toxic. It can be made into a liquid when cooled. It is heavier than air.</advanced><advanced>When sodium and chlorine react, they form Sodium Chloride, or table salt. This reaction is highly exothermic, and produces a yellow glow and alot of heat</advanced><advanced>Table salt is a mineral composed mainly of sodium chloride (NaCl). This is a chemical compound, one of a large number of salts. Salt in its natural form as a crystalline mineral is known as rock salt or halite.</advanced></model>
        //decomposition
        <model><simple>Splitting water</simple><advanced>Water is a simple chemical made from two gases — hydrogen and oxygen. Every molecule of water has two atoms of hydrogen for every atom of oxygen. H2O is the chemical formula for a molecule of water.</advanced><advanced>If an electrical current is passed through water between electrodes (the positive and minus poles of a battery), the water is split into its two parts: oxygen and hydrogen. This process is called electrolysis and is used in industry in many ways, such as making metals like aluminum</advanced></model><model><simple>Decomposing lithium carbonate</simple><advanced>Lithium carbonate is a white solid. It dissolves in water, although not as much as sodium carbonate. It reacts with acids to make carbon dioxide. And it can react with carbon dioxide temporarily to make the bicarbonate.</advanced><advanced>When Lithium carbonate is heated, it decomposes to form Lithium oxide, and carbon dioxide </advanced></model>
        //todo
        <model><simple>Potassium Chloride</simple>2 KCl(s) → 2 K(s) + Cl2
          <advanced>Potassium Chloride has many uses, It is used in food processing, it is used instead of table salt sometimes, and tt can be used to extinguish fires.</advanced><advanced>Potassium Chloride, when heated breaks down into Potassium and Chlorine gas</advanced></model>
        //displacment
        <model><simple>Burning methane</simple><advanced>Combustion (or burning) is a chemical process in which fuel reacts with an oxidant to produce heat. The release of heat can produce light in the form of flame.</advanced><advanced>There are two types of combustiosn, complete and incomplete</advanced><advanced>Fuel reacts with oxygen and release energy. Complete combustion happens in a plentiful supply of air. Incomplete combustion occurs when the supply of air is limited. 
          Complete combustion releases more energy than incomplete combustion. Incomplete combustion also creates carbon monoxide, and more soot. </advanced><advanced>When methane is mixed with oxygen, and heat is supplied, it reacts in a combustion reaction, in this case, a complete combustion reaction is shown</advanced></model><model><simple>Zinc in acid</simple><advanced>Zinc is a metallic element that reacts with hydrochloric acid when it's in its elemental state</advanced><advanced> This reaction generates the very flammable element H2, or hydrogen gas.</advanced><advanced>Not all metals react with acids, if they react, and how much they react depends on their placment on the activity list</advanced></model>
//todo
        <model><simple>Iron and Copper sulfate</simple><advanced>Copper sulfate is a blue solid that can kill fungi. It is also used to purify copper metal. It is common in chemistry sets and chemistry demonstrations.</advanced><advanced>It is a weak oxidizing agent. It reacts with most metals to make copper and a metal sulfate. For example, it reacts with iron to make copper and iron(II) sulfate.</advanced></model>
        
        //double displacment
        <model><simple>Neutralizing an acid</simple><advanced>Neutralization occurs when a base is reacted with an acid. The OH- ions in the base react with the H+ ions in the acid to form H2O, water</advanced><advanced>Neutralization reactions bring the mixtures closer to a pH of 7, which indicates a neutral substance (neither acidic nor basic)</advanced></model>
//todo
        <model><simple>Salt and Silver Nitrate</simple><advanced>Silver nitrate is a colorless crystalline solid. It dissolves in water, despite the fact that most silver compounds do not dissolve in water. It can also get dark if light shines on it, and is an oxidizing agent.</advanced><advanced>The reaction between salt and silver nitrate produces silver chloride and sodium nitrate salt.</advanced></model><model><simple>Baking soda and Vinegar volcano</simple><advanced>This is the classic reaction that produces the baking soda and vinegar volcano</advanced><advanced>Vinegar is a liquid used mostly in cooking. It can be made from wine or other liquids containing alcohol. Vinegar contains about 5% of Acetic acid. The acid makes it sour.</advanced>\
          
          <advanced>Baking soda is a white crystalline powder. It reacts with acids to produce carbon dioxide gas. It also reacts with bases to reduce their harmful effects.</advanced><advanced>When sodium bicarbonate is heated, it releases carbon dioxide and water vapor (gas) and turns into sodium carbonate.</advanced><advanced>When baking soda and vinegar react carbonic acid is produced. However, this acid is very unstable, and falls apart leaving only carbon dioxide and water.</advanced><advanced>Bubbles begin floating around the top of the experiment. The bubbles, produced by this reaction, are actually the carbon dioxide escaping. </advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Kinetic and potential energy" topics="28" level="5" index="104" inq="What are some everyday examples of changes of energy?" score="0"><model><simple>Welcome</simple><advanced>Create your own Gold Ruberg machine to learn about the different types of energies, and how they can be transfered from one form to another</advanced><advanced>You can add objects from the menu on the left, when you are ready, click play!</advanced><advanced>You can also choose from the prebuilt models, to get some ideas for your own machines</advanced><advanced>Want to put your machine to the test? Click the submit button to enter it into the weekly Gold Ruberg competition, and compete for prizes!</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal energy</simple><advanced>Matter is made up of particles or molecules. These molecules move (or vibrate) constantly.</advanced><advanced>A rise in the temperature of matter makes the particles vibrate faster. Thermal energy is what we call energy that comes from the temperature of matter. The hotter the substance, the more its molecules vibrate, and therefore the higher its thermal energy.</advanced><advanced>However, thermal energy and temprature are not the same thing. The temperature of an object is to do with how hot or cold it is and is measured in degrees Celsius (°C). Meanwhile thermal energy depends on the number of molecules, and the temprature, it is meassure in Jolues </advanced><advanced>To understand the differnece, consider the following example: </advanced><advanced>A swimming pool at 40°C is at a lower temperature than a cup of tea at 90°C. However, the swimming pool contains a lot more water. Therefore, the pool has more thermal energy than the cup of tea even though the tea is hotter than the water in the pool.</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic energy</simple><advanced>All moving things have kinetic energy. It is energy possessed by an object due to its motion or movement. </advanced><advanced>These include very large things, like planets, and very small ones, like atoms. The heavier a thing is, and the faster it moves, the more kinetic energy it has.</advanced><advnaced></advnaced></model><model><simple>Mechanical energy</simple><advanced>Mechanical energy is often confused with Kinetic and Potential Energy.</advanced><advanced>Before that, we need to understand the word ‘Work’.</advanced><advanced>‘Work’ is done when a force acts on an object to cause it to move, change shape, displace, or do something physical.</advanced><advanced>For work to be done, the object must move, if you push as hard as you can on a wall, althought you exert a force, you do no work. However, if you move a pencil, althought the force used is smaller, you still do more work, because the pencil moved</advanced><advanced>Mechanical energy is the sum of kinetic and potential energy in an object that is used to do work. In other words, it is energy in an object due to its motion or position, or both.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational energy</simple><advanced> Gravitational Potential energy is stored in the height of the object. Any time that a heavy object is kept high up, a force or power is likely to be holding it up there.</advanced><advanced>Therefore, the higher the object, and the heavier it is, the more gravitational energy it has</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic energy</simple><advanced>Each time energy is transferred into an object, two things happen. It is either used to do work, or it is stored in the object. If it is stored, the object is given potential energy that can be released to do work.</advanced><advanced>Elastic energy is energy stored in stretched or compressed elastic materials.</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Elastic energy can be converted into kinetic energy. In this case the potential elastic energy stored in the spring is converted into kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>In this case, the total mechanical energy of the system remains the same, as no extra energy was created or destoryed, it only changed forms</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Gravitational potential energy can be converted into kinetic energy, or motion.</advanced><advanced>As an object begins to fall, its gravitational energy decreases, but at the same time its kinetic energy increases. In this way, the total energy of the system remains the same</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Thermal energy can be transfered into kinetic energy. The thermal energy causes the molecules in the surrounding area to vibrate and move more, this in turn can push on other objects, causing kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>As the molecules push on some object, or on eachother, they begin to cool. In this way the thermal energy decreases, but the kinetic energy increases the same amount</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to elastic energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into elastic potential energy. This can happen for exmaple when a ball falls on a spring, and compresses it. </advanced><advanced>In this case, the kinetic energy of the ball is 0, as is the spring. However, the same amount of energy is still in the system, except it is now stored as potential energy in the spring</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to gravitational energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into gravitation energy. For example, when you throw a ball in the air as it rises it begins to slow, until eventually it stops and begins to fall again</advanced><advanced>as the ball rises, its kinetic energy begins to become stored in gravitational potential energy. When the ball is at the top of its path, the kinetic energy is 0 (its not moving), this means that all the energy in the system is stored in gravitational potential energy</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to thermal energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into thermal energy.</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Waves" topics="29" level="5" index="95" inq="Sound waves are meassured in Decibals (Db), do some research and find out how loud the loudest sound you heard was, write the answer below!" score="0"><model><simple>Waves</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about basic wave terminology</advanced><advanced>There are lots of waves all around us in everyday life. Sound is a type of wave that moves through matter and then vibrates our eardrums so we can hear. Light is a special kind of wave that is made up of photons. You can drop a rock into a pond and see waves form in the water. We even use waves (microwaves) to cook our food </advanced><advanced>Waves can be divided into various categories depending on their characteristics. All waves can be categorized as either mechanical or electromagnetic.</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Mechanical waves</simple><advanced>Mechanical waves are waves that require a medium. This means that they have to have some sort of matter to travel through. These waves travel when molecules in the medium collide with each other passing on energy.</advanced><advanced>One example of a mechanical wave is sound. Sound can travel through air, water, or solids, but it can't travel through a vacuum. It needs the medium to help it travel. Other examples include water waves, seismic waves, and waves traveling through a spring.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave requries a medium</quiz><quiz>Sound waves are an exmaple of this type of wave</quiz><quiz>This type of wave cannot travel throught a vacuum</quiz><quiz>Water waves is this type of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Electromagnetic waves</simple><advanced>Electromagnetic waves are waves that can travel through a vacuum (empty space). They don't need a medium or matter.</advanced><advanced>They travel through electrical and magnetic fields that are generated by charged particles. Examples of electromagnetic waves include light, microwaves, radio waves, and X-rays.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave doesn't require a medium</quiz><quiz>Microwaves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Radio waves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Light is this kind of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Travelling waves</simple><advanced>Another way to describe a wave is by the direction that its disturbance is traveling. We can categorize waves into two categories, transverse and longitudinal waves</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Transverse waves</simple><advanced>Transverse waves are waves where the disturbance moves perpendicular to the direction of the wave.</advanced><advanced>You can think of the wave moving left to right, while the disturbance moves up and down. One example of a transverse wave is a water wave where the water moves up and down as the wave passes through the ocean.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave causes disturbances perpendicular to the direction of the wave</quiz><quiz>Water waves move in this type of way</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Longitudinal waves</simple><advanced>Longitudinal waves are waves where the disturbance moves in the same direction as the wave.</advanced><advanced>One example of this is a wave moving through a stretched out slinky or spring. If you compress one portion of the slinky and let go, the wave will move left to right. At the same time, the disturbance (which is the coils of the springs moving), will also move left to right.</advanced><advanced> Another classic example of a longitudinal wave is sound. As sound waves propagate through a medium, the molecules collide with each other in the same direction as the sound is moving.</advanced><quiz>Sound waves move in this type of way</quiz><quiz>This type of wave causes a disturbance in the same direction as the wave</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //6
          <simple>Amplitude</simple><advanced>The amplitude of a wave is a measure of the displacement of the wave from its rest position, in other words it is how high/low the wave goes</advanced><advanced>In the case of water waves this can be thought of as the height of the wave, the higher the wave the larger the amplitude</advanced><advanced>The amplitude is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave. For example, when looking at a sound wave, the amplitude will measure the loudness of the sound. The energy of the wave also varies in direct proportion to the amplitude of the wave.</advanced><quiz>This is the measure of the displacement of the wave</quiz><quiz>This can be thought of as the height of the wave</quiz><quiz>This is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave</quiz><quiz>This represents the loudness for sound waves</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //7
          <simple>Wavelength</simple><advanced>The wavelength of a wave is the distance between two corresponding points on back-to-back cycles of a wave.</advanced><advanced>This can be measured between two crests of a wave or two troughs of a wave. The wavelength is usually represented in physics by the Greek letter lambda (λ).</advanced><advanced>In the term of water waves this can be thought of as how "long" the waves are</advanced><quiz>This measures the distance between two corresponding points on back to back cycles of a wave</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //8
          <simple>Frequency and Period</simple><advanced>The frequency of a wave is the number of times per second that the wave cycles. Frequency is measured in Hertz or cycles per second. The frequency is often represented by the lower case "f."</advanced><advanced>The period of the wave is the time between wave crests. The period is measured in time units such as seconds. The period is usually represented by the upper case "T."</advanced><advanced>The period and frequency are closely related to each other. The period equals 1 over the frequency and the frequency is equal to one over the period. They are reciprocals of each other</advanced></model><model section="2">
          //9
          <simple>Velocity of a Wave</simple><advanced>Another important property of a wave is the speed of propagation. This is how fast the disturbance of the wave is moving. </advanced><advanced>The speed of mechanical waves depends on the medium that the wave is traveling through. For example, sound will travel at a different speed in water than in air.</advanced><advanced>velocity = frequency * wavelength or v = f * λ</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Biochemistry" topics="30" level="5" index="87" inq="What is DNA? Summarize your answer below, remember, try to keep it simple!" score="0">
        //ok, so for this one, put it in models, just get the cell model, and have the images of the protiens and all that as particle systems that they can click on
        <model section="1"><simple>Biochemistry</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the basics of carbohydrates, lipids, protiens, and nucleic acid, as well as celular respiration</advanced></model><model><simple>Nucleic Acids</simple><advanced>Nucleic acids are large molecules where genetic information is stored. There are two types of nucleic acids: deoxyribonucleic acid, better known as DNA and ribonucleic acid, better known as RNA.</advanced><advanced>Nucleic acids allow organisms to transfer genetic information from one generation to the next. When a cell divides, its DNA is copied and passed from one cell generation to the next generation.</advanced><advanced>DNA is organized into chromosomes and found within the nucleus of our cells. Its function in any cell is to carry the sequence of bases which will be transcribed into RNA. RNA then has many function within the cell</advanced><quiz>These molecules are responsible for passing on genetic information</quiz><quiz>These molecules are used to create another important molecule known as RNA</quiz><quiz>These molecules are organized into chromosones</quiz></model><model><simple>Carbohydrate</simple><advanced>Carbohydrates are chemical compounds that contain only oxygen, hydrogen and carbon. </advanced><advanced>They are made up of joined-up sugars. Sugars have the general formula Cm(H2O)n, and are also known as saccharides.</advanced><advanced>Certain carbohydrates are an important storage and transport form of energy in most organisms, including plants and animals.</advanced><advanced>Carbohydrates are very good for energy, but, if a person eats more than needed, the extra is changed into fat.</advanced><quiz>These molecules are very good for energy, however if too much of them are eaten, they are changed into fat</quiz><quiz>These molecules are made of joined-up sugars</quiz></model><model><simple>Cellular respiration</simple><advanced>Cellular respiration is what cells do to break up sugars into a form that the cell can use as energy. </advanced><advanced>Cellular respiration takes in food and uses it to create ATP, a chemical which the cell uses for energy. Usually, this process uses oxygen, and is called aerobic respiration.</advanced><advanced>It also produces carbon dioxide as a waste product, which then enters the circulatory system. The carbon dioxide is taken to the lungs, where it is exchanged for oxygen.</advanced><advanced> When they don't get enough oxygen, the cells use anaerobic respiration, which doesn’t require oxygen. However, this process produces lactic acid, and is not as efficient as when oxygen is used. </advanced><advanced>The equation for this process is Glucose (sugar) + Oxygen → Carbon dioxide + Water + Energy (as ATP)</advanced><quiz>Every cell does this to produce energy</quiz></model><model><simple>Protiens</simple><advanced>Proteins are long-chain molecules built from small units known as amino acids. They are joined together with peptide bonds.</advanced><advanced>Proteins are essential to all cells. proteins take part in virtually every process in cells</advanced><advanced>Proteins do different things depending on their shape. They can be found in meat or muscle. They are used for growth and repair, making tissue cells and used for strengthening the bones.</advanced><advanced>There are four things that determine what a protein will do. The first is the order of the amino acids. he second is the little twists in the chain. The third is how the entire thing is folded up. The fourth is whether it is made up of different sub-units</advanced><quiz>These molecules are made up of small units known as amino acids</quiz><quiz>These molecules are found in large numbers in meat and muscle</quiz><quiz>These molecules are used for growth, repair, making tissue cells and strengthening bones amoung others</quiz></model><model><simple>Lipids</simple><advanced>A lipid is a type of organic molecule found in living things. It is oily or waxy. Fats are made from lipid molecules.</advanced><advanced>Sources of lipid can be found in algae, seeds, meat, cheese, butter and fish. </advanced><advanced>Lipids are long chains of carbon and hydrogen molecules. Lipids are classified as simple and complex. Examples of complex molecules could be steroids or phospholipids.</advanced><advanced>A very important biological function of lipids is as lipid bilayers, the basis of many cell membranes. Another function of lipids is to serve as an energy reserve.</advanced><advanced>In summary, lipids are a group of naturally occurring molecules that include fats, waxes, sterols, fat-soluble vitamins (such as vitamins A, D, E, and K), glycerides, phospholipids, and others. The main biological functions of lipids include storing energy, signalling, and acting as components of cell membranes.</advanced><quiz>These molecules naturally occure in fats, waxes and fat-soluble vitamins</quiz><quiz>These molecules are classified as either simple or complex</quiz><quiz>The main functions of this molelcule include signalling, storing energy, and building the cell membrane</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Anatomy and physiology" topics="31" level="5" index="88" inq="What are the effects of alcohol on the body, and escpecially on the liver?" score="0"><model><simple>Heart</simple><advanced>The Heart's function is to pump blood throughout the body</advanced><advanced>The Heart is considered a muscle</advanced><advanced>The heart consists of four different chambers: the left atrium, the right atrium, the left ventricle and the right ventricle.</advanced><quiz>This organ is made up of four different chambers</quiz></model><model><simple>Brain</simple><advanced>The Brain allows us to think, store memories, analyze and make judgments while at the same time controlling other areas automatically, such as breathing.</advanced><advanced>The human brain weighs 3 pounds and is made up of 60% fat. The brain consists of the cerebrum, the brainstem, and the cerebellum.</advanced><advanced>The cerebrum: this is responsible for a number of things like speech, motion, it also controls movement and learning it’s the largest part of the brain.</advanced><advanced>The cerebellum: its main function is for helping with muscle movements, posture and balance</advanced>\
          <advanced>The brainstem: plays a really important function by connecting the cerebrum and cerebellum to your spinal cord. It automatically looks after many of our bodies function like body temperature, digestion, heart rate and even things like sneezing and coughing.</advanced><quiz>This organ controls all of our bodys vital functions</quiz></model><model><simple>Lungs</simple><advanced>Blood runs through our body, goes to the lungs to pick up oxygen from the air we breathe in and then drops off carbon dioxide, which we breathe out.</advanced><advanced>The average adult individual breathes almost 11,000 liters of air every single day.</advanced><advanced>The lungs have special little hairs in tubes in your lungs that move up and out. This helps the special cells that produce mucus. Mucus in the lungs is also specialized as it catches bacteria, dirt and dust that you breathe in as well as bacteria in the air.</advanced><quiz>This organ supplies blood with oxygen, and removes carbon dioxide</quiz></model><model><simple>Liver</simple><advanced>The liver is involved in almost every vital function of the body, such as making and storing energy; producing proteins vital for body function; processing drugs, and playing a vital role in immune function. </advanced><advanced>Your liver is the second largest organ (after the skin), it weights about 3 pounds</advanced><advanced>It's the only organ that can completly regenerate, it only needs 25% of the orignial tissue, and can regrow in less than two weeks</advanced><quiz>It is the second largest organ in the body</quiz></model><model><simple>Kidney</simple><advanced>Kidneys are two bean shaped organs, that are responsible for creating urine</advanced><advanced>Kidneys make hormones. The two most important ones that it makes are erythropoetin and renin.</advanced><advanced>The kidney's most important work is keeping homeostasis. Homeostasis means that the body keeps a stable environment inside itself</advanced><quiz>This organ is important in keeping homeostasis</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Photosynthesis" topics="35" level="5" index="90" inq="Do all plants use photosynthesis? Do some animals use photosynthesis? Write your answers below!" score="0"><model><simple>Carbon Dioxide</simple><advanced>Carbon dioxide is a gas that is present in the air.</advanced><advanced>Plants collect carbon dioxide through tiny holes called stomates.</advanced><advaned>Carbon dioxide is then combined with water and oxygen in a process known as photosynthesis</advaned><quiz>This gas is needed to complete photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Energy from the Sun</simple><advanced>Sunlight is absorbed by a green chemical in the leaves, called chlorophil</advanced><advanced>The energy from the sun is used to split the water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen</advanced><quiz>This source of energy is required for photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Oxygen</simple><advanced>During the process of photosynthesis, stomates are used to expel a gas called oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Oxygen is very important for animals like humans – we need it to breathe!</advanced><quiz>This is biproduct of photosynthesis is expelled by the plant</quiz></model><model><simple>Glucose</simple><advanced>Glucose is a type of sugar, that the plant uses as energy to grow, and reproduce</advanced><advanced>Glucose is produced throught photosynthesis, the word equation would be: Carbon Dioxide + Water + Light Energy = Glucose + Oxygen</advanced><quiz>This is what the plant produces throught photosynthesis, which it uses to grow and reproduce</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Ecological interactions" topics="36" level="5" index="91" inq="How have humans effected some ecologys? Write some examples below!" score="0"><model section="1"><simple>Ecological interaction</simple><advacned>In this module you will learn about the different interactions in a food web and food chain</advacned></model><model section="1"><simple>Food chain</simple><advanced>Every living plant and animal must have energy to survive. Plants rely on the soil, water, and the sun for energy. Animals rely on plants as well as other animals for energy.</advanced><advanced>In an ecosystem, plants and animals all rely on each other to live. Scientists sometimes describe this dependence using a food chain or a food web.</advanced><advanced>A food chain describes how different organisms eat each other, starting out with a plant and ending with an animal. </advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Food Web</simple><advanced>In any ecosystem there are many food chains and, generally, most plants and animals are part of several chains. When you draw all the chains together you end up with a food web.</advanced><quiz>This describes an ecosystem with many food chains</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Trophic Levels</simple><advanced>Sometimes scientists describe each level in a food web with a trophic level. Here are the five trophic levels:</advanced><advanced>   Level 1: Plants (producers)</advanced><advanced>Level 2: Animals that eat plants or herbivores (primary consumers)</advanced><advanced>Level 3: Animals that eat herbivores (secondary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 4: Animals that eat carnivores (tertiary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 5: Animals at the top of the food chain are called apex predators. Nothing eats these animals.</advanced><quiz>These levels describe each level in a food web</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //kelp and plankton
          <simple>Producers </simple><advanced>Plants are producers. This is because they produce energy for the ecosystem.</advanced><advanced>They do this because they absorb energy from sunlight through photosynthesis. They also need water and nutrients from the soil, but plants are the only place where new energy is made.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Primary Consumers</simple> //crab
          <advanced>Animals are consumers. This is because they don't produce energy, they just use it up.</advanced><advanced> Animals that eat plants are called primary consumers or herbivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat plants</quiz><quiz>Another name for these animals is herbivores</quiz></model><model section="2">
          // squid, krill
          <simple>Secondary Consumers</simple><advanced>Animals that eat other animals are called secondary consumers or carnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat herbivores.</quiz><quiz>Another name for these consumers is carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //penguin, walrus, seal, seagull
          <simple>Tertiary Consumer</simple><advanced> If a carnivore eats another carnivore, it is called a tertiary consumer.</advanced><quiz>These are animals that eat other carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Omnivore</simple> //fish
          <advanced>Some animals play both roles, eating both plants and animals. They are called omnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat both plants and animals</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Decomposers</simple> //plankton
          <advanced>Decomposers eat decaying matter (like dead plants and animals). They help put nutrients back into the soil for plants to eat. </advanced><advanced>Examples of decomposers are worms, bacteria, and fungi.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat decaying matter</quiz><quiz>Worms, bacteria and fungi belong to this group</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //killer whale, whale
          <simple>Apex preditor</simple><advanced>Apex predators are predators with no natural predators of their own. They are at the top of their food chain.</advanced><quiz>These animals are at the top of their food chain</quiz><quiz>These animals have not preditors  of their own</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" index="93" inq="Tectonic plates are always moving, can you describe how the world will look in 1,000,000 years? Don't be afraid to look it up!" score="0"><model><simple>Plate Tectonics</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about plate tectonics, their different types, and how they shape our world</advanced></model><model><simple>Divergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In some places, the plates are pulling apart. New crust is pushed up from below. </advanced><advanced> These are called divergent boundaries and they create rifts or valleys.</advanced><advanced>Large lakes sometimes form in rifts.</advanced><quiz>These places create rifts or valleys</quiz></model><model><simple>Convergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In other places the plates are pushing against each other, creating mountains</advanced><advanced> Sometimes one crust is dragged beneath – or subducted – below another one</advanced><advanced>Ocean plates are heavier than continental plates so these plates are always dragged beneath.</advanced><quiz>These boundaries create mountains</quiz></model><model><simple>Transform boundaries</simple><advanced>A transform boundary happens when plates slide past each other but neither collide nor rip apart.</advanced><advanced>The San Andreas Fault in California is a transform boundary.</advanced><quiz>At these boundaries, plates slide past each other</quiz></model></lesson></subject><subject name="Other"><score>100</score><time>20</time><lesson name="Animal Cell" topics="-1" level="5" score="0"></lesson></subject></grade>
  <grade number="6">
    <subject name="math">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
      <lesson name="whole numbers" topics="103,104,105,10,9,107,108,106" level="5" index="25" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="decimals" topics="125,118" level="5" index="28" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="addition and subtraction" topics="1,2" level="5" index="1" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="multiplication and division" topics="3,4,11,100,101,5,6" index="27" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="multiply and divide deicmals" topics="" level="5" index="6" score="0"></lesson> //need to add deicmals
      <lesson name="exponents" topics="27,11,120" level="5" index="45" score="0"></lesson> //find exponents    27 power and roots ladder   11 power of 10   90 index law power of power
      <lesson name="number theory" topics="114,115,15,16,17,18" level="5" index="4" score="0"></lesson> //make this less
      <lesson name="fractions and mixed numbers" topics="20,7,42,59" index="8" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="add subtract fractions" topics="31" level="5" index="10" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="multiply and divide fractions" topics="32" level="5" index="11" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="fractions, decimals and percents" topics="77,78,79,80,81" index="38" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="rational numbers" topics="28" level="5" index="30" score="0"></lesson> //compare rational numbers and put them in order  28 is ordeing
      <lesson name="problem solving and estimation" topics="109" level="5" index="13" score="0"></lesson>  //109 is estimating
      <lesson name="ratios and rates" topics="92,93,94,12,52,19" level="5" index="31" score="0"></lesson> //92-94   ratio reverse 52 ratio share 12   simplyfying 19
      <lesson name="percents" topics="8,49,50,13,95,96" level="5" index="32" score="0"></lesson>  //converting fdp 13 random   interchangin fdp 67 random   77-81 converting and interchanging
      <lesson name="units of measurement" topics="55,56,57,45,74,112,61" index="20" level="5" score="0"></lesson> // 8 percent of an amount   49 percent +-   50 reverse percent   95 percent multip    96 percent change  97 repeated percent change
      <lesson name="money" topics="24,25,53" level="5" index="7" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="time" topics="74,112,110,111,26" level="5" index="19" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="roman numbers" topics="129,130" level="5" index="102" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="number sequences" topics="119" level="5" index="14" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132" level="5" index="26" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="expressions and properties" topics="68,64,65,29,51,30" index="16" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="one-variable equations" topics="29,38,64,65,68,51,66,44" level="5" index="33" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="two-variable equations" topics="" level="5" index="34" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="two-dimensional figures" topics="141,142,143,144,62" index="21" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="symetry and transformation" topics="-1" level="5" index="22" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="three-dimensional figures" topics="149,150" index="23" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="geometic measurment" topics="-1" level="5" index="20" score="0"></lesson>  //
      <lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="statistics and probability" topics="58,63,33,34,35,36,37" index="18" level="5" score="0"></lesson> //you can add a bunch of stuff here 58    expected freq 63   33-37 mean median stuff
    </subject>
    <subject name="science">
      <lesson name="Science practices and tools" topics="23" level="5" index="82" score="0">
        <model>
          <simple>Saftey goggles</simple>
          <advanced>This is the most important piece of saftey equipment</advanced>
          <advanced>You must always where eye protection when working with dangerous chemicals</advanced>
          <quiz>This peice of protective equipment is essential</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Bunsen burner</simple>
          <advanced>The Bunsen burner is a metal tube that produces a flame from gas such as methane, propane, or butane.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is used in the lab for heating and sterilizing.</advanced>
          <advanced>The Bunsen burner is named after German chemist Robert Bunsen.</advanced>
          <quiz>This peice of equipment is used for heating and sterilizing</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Test tube</simple>
          <advanced>A test tube is a glass or plastic tube used for holding, mixing, and heating small quantities of liquid chemicals. </advanced>
          <advanced>Test tubes often have a flared top to help with pouring. They come in a variety of sizes.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used for holding, mixing and heating small quantities of chemicals</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Crucible</simple>
          <advanced> Crucibles are containers used for heating substances to very high temperatures. </advanced>
          <advanced>They are generally made from materials such as porcelain, nickel, and alumina.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used for heating substances to very high temperatures</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Florence flask</simple>
          <advanced>Florence flasks are often used as a container to hold liquids. It has a round body, a long neck, and often a flat bottom.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is designed for uniform heating, boiling, distillation and ease of swirling; it is produced in a number of different glass thicknesses to stand different types of use.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is often used for uniform heating , boiling and distillation</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Erlenmeyer flask</simple>
          <advanced>This is a type of chemistry flask with a conical shaped body, a cylindrically shaped neck, and a flat bottom</advanced>
          <advanced> It generally has measurement marks on the side.</advanced>
          <advanced>The cone shape reduces losses from evaporation and helps to prevent spills when stirring the liquid.</advanced>
          <quiz>It has a cone shape that helps reduce losses from evaporation</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Graduated cylinder</simple>
          <advanced> A tall skinny cylinder used to measure volumes.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is generally a more accurate way to measure volume than a typical beaker or flask.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to accuratly measure volume</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Corks</simple>
          <advanced>Corks are used to block the opening on test tubes. This is done to reduce losses from evaporation, or prevent spills</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to block the opening on test tubes</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Funnel</simple>
          <advanced> A funnel is a pipe with a wide mouth that helps to pour substances into a container without spilling.</advanced>
          <advanced>In a chemistry lab, funnels are often used together with filters to separate a mixture.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used when pouring substances from one container into another</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Pipet</simple>
          <advanced> A narrow glass tube used to transfer liquids from one place to another</advanced>
          <advanced>Pipettes sometimes are used for measurement. The accuracy of different pipettes varies widely.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to transfer liquids from one place to another</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Beaker</simple>
          <advanced>A beaker is a glass container with a flat bottom and a small spout for pouring.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is used in the chemistry lab for mixing, heating, and stirring liquids.</advanced>
          <advanced>Beakers come in various sizes and are shaped like a cylinder.</advanced>
          <quiz>It has a flat bottom and a small spout for pouring</quiz>
        </model>
      </lesson>
      <lesson name="Designing experiments" topics="24" level="5" index="83" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Engineering practices" topics="25" level="5" index="83" score="0"></lesson> //not done, skip?
        <lesson name="Matter and mass" topics="1" level="5" index="62" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Chemical reactions" topics="26" level="5" index="84" score="0"><model><simple>Chemical reactions</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about some common chemical reactions, what they are, and how they work</advanced></model><model><simple>Creating water</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Photosynthesis</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Decomposing water</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Decomposing lithium carbonate</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Burning methane</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Zinc in acid</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Neutralizing an acid</simple><advanced></advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Velocity, acceleration, and forces" topics="27" level="5" index="66" score="0"><model><simple>Newtons laws and gravity</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about Newtons laws, and gravity. By the end of this module you will understand the basics of Newtons laws, and how they apply to the real world example of launching a rocket!</advanced><advanced>First, choose the material and the fuel you would like to use in your rocket. Then click the launch button to launch your rocket! The higher your rocket goes, the more you will learn.</advanced><advanced>To turn off the popups, simple deselect Active Learning the settings menu</advanced></model><model><simple>Steel</simple><advanced>Steel is a mixture of several metals (this is called an alloy) but most of it is iron.</advanced><advanced>Something made of pure iron is softer than steel because the atoms can slip over one another. If other atoms like carbon are added, they are different from iron atoms and stop the iron atoms from sliding apart so easily. This makes the metal stronger and harder.</advanced><advanced>Althought steel is stronger and lighter than iron, it is often not strong or light enough for use in most rockets</advanced></model><model><simple>Aluminium</simple><advanced>Aluminum is a chemical element. It is the most abundant metal, and is known for its resistance to corrosion and its light weight.</advanced><advanced> Aluminum, however, melts at the high reentry temperatures. So, if a rocket needs to come back to Earth (like the Space Shuttle), heat shield tiles are added</advanced></model><model><simple>Titanium</simple><advanced>Titanium is a very strong metal. It is chemical element number 22 on the periodic table </advanced><advanced>Titanium is used for making the strongest and lightest parts of fighter jets, aircraft, and rockets</advanced><advanced>However, it can burn at high temperatures, and titanium dust is extremely flammable. </advanced></model><model><simple>Carbon composite</simple><advanced> It has the highest compressive strength of all the reinforcing materials (composites), and it has a high strength to weight ratio and low coefficient of thermal expansion</advanced><advanced> The density of carbon fiber is also much lower than the density of steel.</advanced><advanced>Carbon fiber is in the form of several thousand long, thin strands of material that is composed of mostly carbon atoms.</advanced></model><model><simple>Spring</simple><advanced>Spring propelled rockets use the potential energy stored in a compressed spring, to form kinetic energy, and launch the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These types of rockets are easy to make at home, however, they do not go very high!</advanced></model><model><simple>Compressed air</simple><advanced>Compressed air rockets use the pressure of a compressed air tank, to form kinetic energy launching the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These systems are more powerful then spring powered ones, however, they </advanced><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Solid fuel</simple><advanced>Solid rocket fuels are those in which the fuel and oxidiser compounds are already combined.</advanced><advanced>Most use an aluminium powder as the fuel and an ammonium perchlorate as the oxidiser, while an iron powder is used as a catalyst for the reaction.</advanced><advaced>Solid fuels are generally used more for the initial launch sequence, when the speed needs to be at its maximum, whereas liquid fuels are used later so the speed can be adjusted to get the rocket’s payload on to the right trajectory.</advaced></model><model><simple>Liquid fuel</simple><advanced>Liquid propellants separate fuel and oxidisers and the two are combined in a combustion chamber where they burn and are ﬁred out from the base of the rocket.</advanced><advanced>iquid fuels are further subcategorised into either petroleum, cryogens or hypergols.</advanced><advanced>Petroleum is fuel derived from crude oil and hydrocarbons, it consists of a highly refined kerosene mixed with liquid oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Cryogens are those stored at very low temperatures (such as liquid hydrogen)</advanced><advanced>Hypergols are able to self-ignite on contact between the fuel and the oxidiser.  These fuels simply needs nitric acid in order to ignite and are frequently used for propulsion when out in space.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravity</simple><advanced>Gravity is one of the four fundamental forces of nature, althought it is the weakest of these four forces, it is important to life on Earth and the structure of the universe.</advanced><advanced>Everything that has matter generates gravity, from a grain of sand to the largest objects in the universe. The larger an object is, the stronger its force</advanced><advanced>In order for a rocket to reach space, the force it exerts up, must be more than the force of gravity pulling it down</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Third Law</simple><advanced>Rocket fuel works on the basis of Newton’s Third Law of Motion, which states that ‘every action is accompanied by an equal and opposite reaction'.</advanced><advanced>By ﬁring fuel out the back of a rocket, the force propels it upwards with acceleration equal to the force at which the fuel is expelled.</advanced><quiz>This law states that every action has an equal and opposite reaction</quiz><quiz>Rockets are based on this law, it is what causes the rocket to be pushed up, when the exahust is pushed down</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Second Law</simple><advanced>Newtons Second Law says that the acceleration of an object produced by a net (total) applied force is directly related to the magnitude of the force, the same direction as the force, and inversely related to the mass of the object</advanced><quiz>This law states that aceleration is directly related to the force, and inversly related to the mass of an object</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that it is harder to push heavier things </quiz></model><model><simple>Space</simple><advanced>Space begins about 100 km (62 miles) above Earth's surface.</advanced><advanced>However, the space around Earth is not empty. There are many artificial satellites, about 5000, these are used for gather information, navigation, and communication amoung other things.</advanced><advanced>There is also a large amount of space junk. Space junk is any human-made object orbiting Earth that no longer serves a useful purpose. Scientists estimate there are about 500,000 pieces of space junk today.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons First Law</simple><advanced>Newtons First Law says that an object at rest tends to stay at rest, and an object in motion tends to stay in motion, with the same direction and speed</advanced><advanced>For example, if you watch videos of astronauts in space, you will notice that their tools float, and they wont move unless the astronaut pushes or pulls it, at which point it will keep moving until it is stopped</advanced><quiz>This law states that an object will stay at rest, or continue in motion unless acted on by an external force</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that objects stay in one spot in space</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Slower</simple><quiz>If a rocket was launched from jupiter, (where the gravity is higher) would it be faster, slower orthe same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Faster</simple><quiz>If the same rocket was launched from the moon (where gravity is lower) would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a lighter material was used for the rocket body would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a you push a small object with some force, and then push a larger object with the same force, will the larger object go faster, slower or the same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Same speed</simple><quiz>If a rocket runs out of fuel in space, but it is moving foward, in 1000 years, will it be travelling faster, slower or at the same speed?</quiz></model></lesson> //this one should not be rocket
        <lesson name="Kinetic and potential energy" topics="28" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Welcome</simple><advanced>Create your own Gold Ruberg machine to learn about the different types of energies, and how they can be transfered from one form to another</advanced><advanced>You can add objects from the menu on the left, when you are ready, click play!</advanced><advanced>You can also choose from the prebuilt models, to get some ideas for your own machines</advanced><advanced>Want to put your machine to the test? Click the submit button to enter it into the weekly Gold Ruberg competition, and compete for prizes!</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal energy</simple><advanced>Matter is made up of particles or molecules. These molecules move (or vibrate) constantly.</advanced><advanced>A rise in the temperature of matter makes the particles vibrate faster. Thermal energy is what we call energy that comes from the temperature of matter. The hotter the substance, the more its molecules vibrate, and therefore the higher its thermal energy.</advanced><advanced>However, thermal energy and temprature are not the same thing. The temperature of an object is to do with how hot or cold it is and is measured in degrees Celsius (°C). Meanwhile thermal energy depends on the number of molecules, and the temprature, it is meassure in Jolues </advanced><advanced>To understand the differnece, consider the following example: </advanced><advanced>A swimming pool at 40°C is at a lower temperature than a cup of tea at 90°C. However, the swimming pool contains a lot more water. Therefore, the pool has more thermal energy than the cup of tea even though the tea is hotter than the water in the pool.</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic energy</simple><advanced>All moving things have kinetic energy. It is energy possessed by an object due to its motion or movement. </advanced><advanced>These include very large things, like planets, and very small ones, like atoms. The heavier a thing is, and the faster it moves, the more kinetic energy it has.</advanced><advnaced></advnaced></model><model><simple>Mechanical energy</simple><advanced>Mechanical energy is often confused with Kinetic and Potential Energy.</advanced><advanced>Before that, we need to understand the word ‘Work’.</advanced><advanced>‘Work’ is done when a force acts on an object to cause it to move, change shape, displace, or do something physical.</advanced><advanced>For work to be done, the object must move, if you push as hard as you can on a wall, althought you exert a force, you do no work. However, if you move a pencil, althought the force used is smaller, you still do more work, because the pencil moved</advanced><advanced>Mechanical energy is the sum of kinetic and potential energy in an object that is used to do work. In other words, it is energy in an object due to its motion or position, or both.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational energy</simple><advanced> Gravitational Potential energy is stored in the height of the object. Any time that a heavy object is kept high up, a force or power is likely to be holding it up there.</advanced><advanced>Therefore, the higher the object, and the heavier it is, the more gravitational energy it has</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic energy</simple><advanced>Each time energy is transferred into an object, two things happen. It is either used to do work, or it is stored in the object. If it is stored, the object is given potential energy that can be released to do work.</advanced><advanced>Elastic energy is energy stored in stretched or compressed elastic materials.</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Elastic energy can be converted into kinetic energy. In this case the potential elastic energy stored in the spring is converted into kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>In this case, the total mechanical energy of the system remains the same, as no extra energy was created or destoryed, it only changed forms</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Gravitational potential energy can be converted into kinetic energy, or motion.</advanced><advanced>As an object begins to fall, its gravitational energy decreases, but at the same time its kinetic energy increases. In this way, the total energy of the system remains the same</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Thermal energy can be transfered into kinetic energy. The thermal energy causes the molecules in the surrounding area to vibrate and move more, this in turn can push on other objects, causing kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>As the molecules push on some object, or on eachother, they begin to cool. In this way the thermal energy decreases, but the kinetic energy increases the same amount</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to elastic energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into elastic potential energy. This can happen for exmaple when a ball falls on a spring, and compresses it. </advanced><advanced>In this case, the kinetic energy of the ball is 0, as is the spring. However, the same amount of energy is still in the system, except it is now stored as potential energy in the spring</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to gravitational energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into gravitation energy. For example, when you throw a ball in the air as it rises it begins to slow, until eventually it stops and begins to fall again</advanced><advanced>as the ball rises, its kinetic energy begins to become stored in gravitational potential energy. When the ball is at the top of its path, the kinetic energy is 0 (its not moving), this means that all the energy in the system is stored in gravitational potential energy</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to thermal energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into thermal energy.</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Thermal energy" topics="2" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Waves" topics="29" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Waves</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about basic wave terminology</advanced><advanced>
              There are lots of waves all around us in everyday life. Sound is a type of wave that moves through matter and then vibrates our eardrums so we can hear.
              Light is a special kind of wave that is made up of photons. You can drop a rock into a pond and see waves form in the water. We even use waves (microwaves) to cook our food
            </advanced><advanced>Waves can be divided into various categories depending on their characteristics. All waves can be categorized as either mechanical or electromagnetic.</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Mechanical waves</simple><advanced>Mechanical waves are waves that require a medium. This means that they have to have some sort of matter to travel through. These waves travel when molecules in the medium collide with each other passing on energy.</advanced><advanced>One example of a mechanical wave is sound. Sound can travel through air, water, or solids, but it can't travel through a vacuum. It needs the medium to help it travel. Other examples include water waves, seismic waves, and waves traveling through a spring.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave requries a medium</quiz><quiz>Sound waves are an exmaple of this type of wave</quiz><quiz>This type of wave cannot travel throught a vacuum</quiz><quiz>Water waves is this type of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Electromagnetic waves</simple><advanced>Electromagnetic waves are waves that can travel through a vacuum (empty space). They don't need a medium or matter.</advanced><advanced>They travel through electrical and magnetic fields that are generated by charged particles. Examples of electromagnetic waves include light, microwaves, radio waves, and X-rays.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave doesn't require a medium</quiz><quiz>Microwaves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Radio waves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Light is this kind of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Travelling waves</simple><advanced>Another way to describe a wave is by the direction that its disturbance is traveling. We can categorize waves into two categories, transverse and longitudinal waves</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Transverse waves</simple><advanced>Transverse waves are waves where the disturbance moves perpendicular to the direction of the wave.</advanced><advanced>You can think of the wave moving left to right, while the disturbance moves up and down. One example of a transverse wave is a water wave where the water moves up and down as the wave passes through the ocean.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave causes disturbances perpendicualr to the direction of the wave</quiz><quiz>Water waves move in this type of way</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Longitudinal waves</simple><advanced>Longitudinal waves are waves where the disturbance moves in the same direction as the wave.</advanced><advanced>One example of this is a wave moving through a stretched out slinky or spring. If you compress one portion of the slinky and let go, the wave will move left to right. At the same time, the disturbance (which is the coils of the springs moving), will also move left to right.</advanced><advanced> Another classic example of a longitudinal wave is sound. As sound waves propagate through a medium, the molecules collide with each other in the same direction as the sound is moving.</advanced><quiz>Sound waves move in this type of way</quiz><quiz>This type of wave causes a disturbance in the same direction as the wave</quiz></model><model section="2"> //6
            <simple>Amplitude</simple><advanced>The amplitude of a wave is a measure of the displacement of the wave from its rest position, in other words it is how high/low the wave goes</advanced><advanced>In the case of water waves this can be thought of as the height of the wave, the higher the wave the larger the amplitude</advanced><advanced>The amplitude is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave. For example, when looking at a sound wave, the amplitude will measure the loudness of the sound. The energy of the wave also varies in direct proportion to the amplitude of the wave.</advanced><quiz>This is the measure of the displacement of the wave</quiz><quiz>This can be thought of as the height of the wave</quiz><quiz>This is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave</quiz><quiz>This represents the loudness for sound waves</quiz></model><model section="2"> //7
            <simple>Wavelength</simple><advanced>The wavelength of a wave is the distance between two corresponding points on back-to-back cycles of a wave.</advanced><advanced>This can be measured between two crests of a wave or two troughs of a wave. The wavelength is usually represented in physics by the Greek letter lambda (λ).</advanced><advanced>In the term of water waves this can be thought of as how "long" the waves are</advanced><quiz>This measures the distance between two corresponding points on back to back cycles of a wave</quiz></model><model section="2"> //8
            <simple>Frequency and Period</simple><advanced>The frequency of a wave is the number of times per second that the wave cycles. Frequency is measured in Hertz or cycles per second. The frequency is often represented by the lower case "f."</advanced><advanced>The period of the wave is the time between wave crests. The period is measured in time units such as seconds. The period is usually represented by the upper case "T."</advanced><advanced>The period and frequency are closely related to each other. The period equals 1 over the frequency and the frequency is equal to one over the period. They are reciprocals of each other</advanced></model><model section="2"> //9
            <simple>Velocity of a Wave</simple><advanced>Another important property of a wave is the speed of propagation. This is how fast the disturbance of the wave is moving. </advanced><advanced>The speed of mechanical waves depends on the medium that the wave is traveling through. For example, sound will travel at a different speed in water than in air.</advanced><advanced>velocity = frequency * wavelength or v = f * λ</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Solutions" topics="4" level="5" score="0"></lesson> //difference between this and mixtures?
        <lesson name="Classification" topics="8" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Classifcation</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the history of taxonomy, and how we calssify all living things</advanced></model><model><simple>Carolus Linnaeus</simple><advanced>Back in the 18th century, a Swedish man named Carolus Linnaeus thought it was important to organize living things, and he developed a system to do just that. </advanced><advanced>His system first only contained plants, however, he quickly expanded it to include all living organisms. We still use the essence of his system today. Scientists are constantly refining the system based on new knowledge. </advanced><advanced>Putting animals in order like this is called taxonomy. The taxonomists — people who name animals — use a book called the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, or ICZN, to tell them the rules for classifying animals.</advanced></model><model><simple>Linnaeus’s system</simple><advanced> His system has seven levels: Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, and Species</advanced><advanced>Every animal on the planet, down to the most microscopic creature you can imagine, can be classified according to this system.</advanced><advanced>An easy way to remember the order is to use the memonic: King Phillip, come out, for goodness’ sake!</advanced></model><model><simple>Kingdom</simple><advanced>Generally, scientists agree there are six kingdoms. The animal kingdom (called Kingdom Animalia) is just one of those. </advanced><advanced>The others are Achaebacteria, Eubacteria, Protists, Fungi and Plants.</advanced><advanced>Originally, Linnaeus only identified two kingdoms: plant and animal. Some scientists think that viruses should have their own kingdom, but currently they are not included under this system.</advanced></model><model><simple>Phylum</simple><advanced>Within the animal kingdom, the animals are divided into more than 30 phyla (which is the plural of “phylum”). </advanced><advanced>Some of the better known phyla are Phylum Chordata and Phylum Arthropoda. Phylum Chordata is the one humans and all animals with backbones are in.</advanced><advanced>Phylum Arthropoda contains insects, spiders and other animals with segmented bodies, like shrimp.  Arthropods have their skeletons on the outside of their bodies (think of the hard shell of a lobster) and other characteristics in common. </advanced></model><model><simple>Class</simple><advanced>The third level of classification is class. For example, Phylum Chordata has classes in it like birds, mammals (Mammalia) and reptiles.</advanced></model><model><simple>Order</simple><advanced>The next level, or rank, is order. Orders are smaller groups within the different classes.</advanced><advanced>Different orders include Lepidoptera and Carnivora. Lepidoptera is the order of moths and butterflies. Carnivora is the order within Mammalia that has the most diversity in animal size.</advanced></model><model><simple>Family</simple><advanced>The fifth rank of classification is family. </advanced></model><model><simple>Genus</simple><advanced>Genus the second-to-last rank, and a genus may have only one or two animals in it. If animals are in the same genus, they are really closely related. </advanced><advanced> In fact, you may not be able to tell them apart just by looking at them! When we write the name of the genus, we capitalize it and italicize it.</advanced><advanced>For example, the genus of dogs (and wolves, too!) is Canis.</advanced></model><model><simple>Species</simple><advanced>If animals can breed together successfully, they are a species. When an animal is called by its scientific name, then that means it is being identified by its genus and species. </advanced><advanced> We use a lowercase letter and italics for the species. </advanced><advanced>For example, the scientific name of dogs is Canis familiaris; however, the scientific name of wolves is Canis lupus.</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Scientific Names" topics="9" level="5" score="0"><model section="1"><simple>Scientific Names</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about common scientific names </advanced></model><model><simple>Modern Humans</simple><advanced>Homo sapiens</advanced><quiz>Homo sapiens</quiz></model><model><simple>African elephant</simple><advanced>Loxodonta africana</advanced><quiz>Loxodonta africana</quiz></model><model><simple>Black rat</simple><advanced>Rattus rattus</advanced><quiz>Rattus rattus</quiz></model><model><simple>Cat</simple><advanced>Felis domesticus</advanced><quiz>Felis domesticus</quiz></model><model><simple>Dog</simple><advanced>Canis lupus familiaris</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus familiaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Horse</simple><advanced>Equus caballus</advanced><quiz>Equus caballus</quiz></model><model><simple>Lion</simple><advanced>Panthera leo</advanced><quiz>Panthera leo</quiz></model><model><simple>Wolf</simple><advanced>Canis lupus</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus</quiz></model><model><simple>Apple</simple><advanced>Malus pumila</advanced><quiz>Malus pumila</quiz></model><model><simple>Carrot</simple><advanced>Daucas carota</advanced><quiz>Daucas carota</quiz></model><model><simple>Lemon</simple><advanced>Citrus limonium</advanced><quiz>Citrus limonium</quiz></model><model><simple>Lettuce</simple><advanced>Lactuca sativa</advanced><quiz>Lactuca sativa</quiz></model><model><simple>Potato</simple><advanced>Solanum tubersum</advanced><quiz>Solanum tubersum</quiz></model><model><simple>Watermelon</simple><advanced>Citrullus vulgaris</advanced><quiz>Citrullus vulgaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Wheat</simple><advanced>Triticum aestivum</advanced><quiz>Triticum aestivum</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Energy Sources" topics="42" level="5" index="86" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Biochemistry" topics="30" level="5" index="87" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Animal Cell" topics="14" level="5" index="71" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plant Cell" topics="15" level="5" index="72" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Anatomy and physiology" topics="31" level="5" index="88" score="0"><model><simple>Heart</simple><advanced>The Heart's function is to pump blood throughout the body</advanced><advanced>The Heart is considered a muscle</advanced><advanced>The heart consists of four different chambers: the left atrium, the right atrium, the left ventricle and the right ventricle.</advanced><quiz>This organ is made up of four different chambers</quiz></model><model><simple>Brain</simple><advanced>The Brain allows us to think, store memories, analyze and make judgments while at the same time controlling other areas automatically, such as breathing.</advanced><advanced>The human brain weighs 3 pounds and is made up of 60% fat. The brain consists of the cerebrum, the brainstem, and the cerebellum.</advanced><advanced>The cerebrum: this is responsible for a number of things like speech, motion, it also controls movement and learning it’s the largest part of the brain.</advanced><advanced>The cerebellum: its main function is for helping with muscle movements, posture and balance</advanced>\
            <advanced>The brainstem: plays a really important function by connecting the cerebrum and cerebellum to your spinal cord. It automatically looks after many of our bodies function like body temperature, digestion, heart rate and even things like sneezing and coughing.</advanced><quiz>This organ controls all of our bodys vital functions</quiz></model><model><simple>Lungs</simple><advanced>Blood runs through our body, goes to the lungs to pick up oxygen from the air we breathe in and then drops off carbon dioxide, which we breathe out.</advanced><advanced>The average adult individual breathes almost 11,000 liters of air every single day.</advanced><advanced>The lungs have special little hairs in tubes in your lungs that move up and out. This helps the special cells that produce mucus. Mucus in the lungs is also specialized as it catches bacteria, dirt and dust that you breathe in as well as bacteria in the air.</advanced><quiz>This organ supplies blood with oxygen, and removes carbon dioxide</quiz></model><model><simple>Liver</simple><advanced>The liver is involved in almost every vital function of the body, such as making and storing energy; producing proteins vital for body function; processing drugs, and playing a vital role in immune function. </advanced><advanced>Your liver is the second largest organ (after the skin), it weights about 3 pounds</advanced><advanced>It's the only organ that can completly regenerate, it only needs 25% of the orignial tissue, and can regrow in less than two weeks</advanced><quiz>It is the second largest organ in the body</quiz></model><model><simple>Kidney</simple><advanced>Kidneys are two bean shaped organs, that are responsible for creating urine</advanced><advanced>Kidneys make hormones. The two most important ones that it makes are erythropoetin and renin.</advanced><advanced>The kidney's most important work is keeping homeostasis. Homeostasis means that the body keeps a stable environment inside itself</advanced><quiz>This organ is important in keeping homeostasis</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Fossils" topics="19" level="5" index="78" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plant reproduction" topics="34" level="5" index="89" score="0"><model><simple>Seed</simple><advanced>Inside a seed is an embryo, which is a tiny plant, and the endosperm, which are small leaves which supply the embryo food. The outside of the seed has a seed coat, which protects the embryo from injury or drying out.</advanced><advanced>All seeds need moisture, oxygen and the right temperature to germinate, or grow. Until they have these conditions, the seed remains dormant and does nothing.</advanced><quiz>This is where all plants start their lives</quiz></model><model><simple>Male flower</simple><advanced> Pollen is the male cell - it's the yellow dust made on the stamen, or male reproductive part, of the flower. </advanced></model><model><simple>Female Flower</simple><advanced>The female part is called the pistil, which contains the ovaries that produce eggs, and it's located in the center of the flower.</advanced><advanced>The pistil also contains the stigma, a sticky bulb that the pollen attaches itself to.</advanced></model></lesson> //add this
        <lesson name="Photosynthesis" topics="35" level="5" index="90" score="0"><model><simple>Carbon Dioxide</simple><advanced>Carbon dioxide is a gas that is present in the air.</advanced><advanced>Plants collect carbon dioxide through tiny holes called stomates.</advanced><advaned>Carbon dioxide is then combined with water and oxygen in a process known as photosynthesis</advaned><quiz>This gas is needed to complete photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Energy from the Sun</simple><advanced>Sunlight is absorbed by a green chemical in the leaves, called chlorophil</advanced><advanced>The energy from the sun is used to split the water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen</advanced><quiz>This source of energy is required for photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Oxygen</simple><advanced>During the process of photosynthesis, stomates are used to expel a gas called oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Oxygen is very important for animals like humans – we need it to breathe!</advanced><quiz>This is biproduct of photosynthesis is expelled by the plant</quiz></model><model><simple>Glucose</simple><advanced>Glucose is a type of sugar, that the plant uses as energy to grow, and reproduce</advanced><advanced>Glucose is produced throught photosynthesis, the word equation would be: Carbon Dioxide + Water + Light Energy = Glucose + Oxygen</advanced><quiz>This is what the plant produces throught photosynthesis, which it uses to grow and reproduce</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Ecosystems" topics="41" level="5" index="73" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Ecology" topics="16" level="5" index="74" score="0"></lesson> //not done
        <lesson name="Ecological interactions" topics="36" level="5" index="91" score="0"><model><simple>Ecological interaction</simple><advacned>In this module you will learn about the different interactions in a food web and food chain</advacned></model><model section="1"><simple>Food chain</simple><advanced>Every living plant and animal must have energy to survive. Plants rely on the soil, water, and the sun for energy. Animals rely on plants as well as other animals for energy.</advanced><advanced>In an ecosystem, plants and animals all rely on each other to live. Scientists sometimes describe this dependence using a food chain or a food web.</advanced><advanced>A food chain describes how different organisms eat each other, starting out with a plant and ending with an animal. </advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Food Web</simple><advanced>In any ecosystem there are many food chains and, generally, most plants and animals are part of several chains. When you draw all the chains together you end up with a food web.</advanced><quiz>This describes an ecosystem with many food chains</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Trophic Levels</simple><advanced>Sometimes scientists describe each level in a food web with a trophic level. Here are the five trophic levels:</advanced><advanced>   Level 1: Plants (producers)</advanced><advanced>Level 2: Animals that eat plants or herbivores (primary consumers)</advanced><advanced>Level 3: Animals that eat herbivores (secondary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 4: Animals that eat carnivores (tertiary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 5: Animals at the top of the food chain are called apex predators. Nothing eats these animals.</advanced><quiz>These levels describe each level in a food web</quiz></model><model section="2"> //kelp and plankton
            <simple>Producers </simple><advanced>Plants are producers. This is because they produce energy for the ecosystem.</advanced><advanced>They do this because they absorb energy from sunlight through photosynthesis. They also need water and nutrients from the soil, but plants are the only place where new energy is made.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Primary Consumers</simple> //crab
            <advanced>Animals are consumers. This is because they don't produce energy, they just use it up.</advanced><advanced> Animals that eat plants are called primary consumers or herbivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat plants</quiz><quiz>Another name for these animals is herbivores</quiz></model><model section="2"> // squid, krill
            <simple>Secondary Consumers</simple><advanced>Animals that eat other animals are called secondary consumers or carnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat herbivores.</quiz><quiz>Another name for these consumers is carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2">  //penguin, walrus, seal, seagull
            <simple>Tertiary Consumer</simple><advanced> If a carnivore eats another carnivore, it is called a tertiary consumer.</advanced><quiz>These are animals that eat other carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Omnivore</simple> //fish
            <advanced>Some animals play both roles, eating both plants and animals. They are called omnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat both plants and animals</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Decomposers</simple> //plankton
            <advanced>Decomposers eat decaying matter (like dead plants and animals). They help put nutrients back into the soil for plants to eat. </advanced><advanced>Examples of decomposers are worms, bacteria, and fungi.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat decaying matter</quiz><quiz>Worms, bacteria and fungi belong to this group</quiz></model><model section="2"> //killer whale, whale
            <simple>Apex preditor</simple><advanced>Apex predators are predators with no natural predators of their own. They are at the top of their food chain.</advanced><quiz>These animals are at the top of their food chain</quiz><quiz>These animals have not preditors  of their own</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Natural resources and human impacts" topics="37" level="5" index="92" score="0"></lesson> //not done
        <lesson name="Rocks and minerals" topics="18" level="5" index="77" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" index="93" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Topographic maps" topics="39" level="5" inex="94" score="0"></lesson> //not done
        <lesson name="Water cycle" topics="21" level="5" index="80" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Plate Tectonics</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about plate tectonics, their different types, and how they shape our world</advanced></model><model><simple>Divergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In some places, the plates are pulling apart. New crust is pushed up from below. </advanced><advanced> These are called divergent boundaries and they create rifts or valleys.</advanced><advanced>Large lakes sometimes form in rifts.</advanced><quiz>These places create rifts or valleys</quiz></model><model><simple>Convergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In other places the plates are pushing against each other, creating mountains</advanced><advanced> Sometimes one crust is dragged beneath – or subducted – below another one</advanced><advanced>Ocean plates are heavier than continental plates so these plates are always dragged beneath.</advanced><quiz>These boundaries create mountains</quiz></model><model><simple>Transform boundaries</simple><advanced>A transform boundary happens when plates slide past each other but neither collide nor rip apart.</advanced><advanced>The San Andreas Fault in California is a transform boundary.</advanced><quiz>At these boundaries, plates slide past each other</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Weather and climate" topics="20" level="5" index="79" score="0"></lesson> //not done
        <lesson name="Astronomy" topics="22" level="5" index="81" score="0"></lesson></subject>
    <subject name="Other">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="7">
    <subject name="math">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
      <lesson name="number theory" topics="114,115,15,16,17,18" level="5" index="4" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="integers" topics="15,16,17,18,23,98,99,10,60,100,101" index="35" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="decimals" topics="121,126,118" level="5" index="28" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="fractions and mixed numbers" topics="7,20,42" index="8" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="add subtract fractions" topics="31" level="5" index="10" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="multiply and divide fractions" topics="32" level="5" index="11" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="fractions, decimals and percents" topics="77,78,79,80,81" index="38" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="rational numbers" topics="28" index="30" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="exponents and square roots" topics="27,11,120" level="5" index="36" score="0"></lesson> //you need to add square roots 
      <lesson name="ratios and rates and proportions" topics="92,93,94,12,52,19" level="5" index="31" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="proportional relationships" topics="" level="5" index="37" score="0"></lesson> //need to make this
      <lesson name="percents" topics="8,49,50,13,95,96,67" level="5" index="32" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="problem solving and estimation" topics="109" level="5" index="13" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="units of measurement" topics="55,56,57,45,74,112,122" index="20" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132,142,151,152" level="5" index="15" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="number sequences" topics="21,22,71,72,47,119" level="5" index="14" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="expressions and properties" topics="68,64,65,29,51,14" level="5" index="16" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="one-variable equations" topics="29,38,64,65,68,51,66,44,46,124" level="5" index="33" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="two-variable equations" topics="" level="5" index="34" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="two-dimensional figures" topics="141,142,143,144,62" level="5" index="21" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="transformations and congruence" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson> //ned to make
      <lesson name="constructions" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson> //not done, need to make
      <lesson name="three-dimensional figures" topics="149,150" level="5" index="23" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="geometic measurment" topics="-1" level="5" index="20" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138,134,135,136" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="statistics and probability" topics="58,63,33,34,35,36,37" level="5" index="18" score="0"></lesson></subject>
    <subject name="science">
      <lesson name="Science practices and tools" topics="23" level="5" index="82" score="0">
        <model>
          <simple>Saftey goggles</simple>
          <advanced>This is the most important piece of saftey equipment</advanced>
          <advanced>You must always where eye protection when working with dangerous chemicals</advanced>
          <quiz>This peice of protective equipment is essential</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Bunsen burner</simple>
          <advanced>The Bunsen burner is a metal tube that produces a flame from gas such as methane, propane, or butane.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is used in the lab for heating and sterilizing.</advanced>
          <advanced>The Bunsen burner is named after German chemist Robert Bunsen.</advanced>
          <quiz>This peice of equipment is used for heating and sterilizing</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Test tube</simple>
          <advanced>A test tube is a glass or plastic tube used for holding, mixing, and heating small quantities of liquid chemicals. </advanced>
          <advanced>Test tubes often have a flared top to help with pouring. They come in a variety of sizes.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used for holding, mixing and heating small quantities of chemicals</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Crucible</simple>
          <advanced> Crucibles are containers used for heating substances to very high temperatures. </advanced>
          <advanced>They are generally made from materials such as porcelain, nickel, and alumina.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used for heating substances to very high temperatures</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Florence flask</simple>
          <advanced>Florence flasks are often used as a container to hold liquids. It has a round body, a long neck, and often a flat bottom.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is designed for uniform heating, boiling, distillation and ease of swirling; it is produced in a number of different glass thicknesses to stand different types of use.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is often used for uniform heating , boiling and distillation</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Erlenmeyer flask</simple>
          <advanced>This is a type of chemistry flask with a conical shaped body, a cylindrically shaped neck, and a flat bottom</advanced>
          <advanced> It generally has measurement marks on the side.</advanced>
          <advanced>The cone shape reduces losses from evaporation and helps to prevent spills when stirring the liquid.</advanced>
          <quiz>It has a cone shape that helps reduce losses from evaporation</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Graduated cylinder</simple>
          <advanced> A tall skinny cylinder used to measure volumes.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is generally a more accurate way to measure volume than a typical beaker or flask.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to accuratly measure volume</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Corks</simple>
          <advanced>Corks are used to block the opening on test tubes. This is done to reduce losses from evaporation, or prevent spills</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to block the opening on test tubes</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Funnel</simple>
          <advanced> A funnel is a pipe with a wide mouth that helps to pour substances into a container without spilling.</advanced>
          <advanced>In a chemistry lab, funnels are often used together with filters to separate a mixture.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used when pouring substances from one container into another</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Pipet</simple>
          <advanced> A narrow glass tube used to transfer liquids from one place to another</advanced>
          <advanced>Pipettes sometimes are used for measurement. The accuracy of different pipettes varies widely.</advanced>
          <quiz>This is used to transfer liquids from one place to another</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Beaker</simple>
          <advanced>A beaker is a glass container with a flat bottom and a small spout for pouring.</advanced>
          <advanced>It is used in the chemistry lab for mixing, heating, and stirring liquids.</advanced>
          <advanced>Beakers come in various sizes and are shaped like a cylinder.</advanced>
          <quiz>It has a flat bottom and a small spout for pouring</quiz>
        </model>
      </lesson>
      <lesson name="Designing experiments" topics="24" level="5" index="83" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Engineering practices" topics="25" level="5" index="83" score="0"></lesson> //not done, skip?
      <lesson name="Matter and mass" topics="1" level="5" index="62" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Chemical reactions" topics="26" level="5" index="84" score="0"><model><simple>Chemical reactions</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about some common chemical reactions, what they are, and how they work</advanced></model><model><simple>Creating water</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Photosynthesis</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Decomposing water</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Decomposing lithium carbonate</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Burning methane</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Zinc in acid</simple><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Neutralizing an acid</simple><advanced></advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Velocity, acceleration, and forces" topics="27" level="5" index="66" score="0"><model><simple>Newtons laws and gravity</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about Newtons laws, and gravity. By the end of this module you will understand the basics of Newtons laws, and how they apply to the real world example of launching a rocket!</advanced><advanced>First, choose the material and the fuel you would like to use in your rocket. Then click the launch button to launch your rocket! The higher your rocket goes, the more you will learn.</advanced><advanced>To turn off the popups, simple deselect Active Learning the settings menu</advanced></model><model><simple>Steel</simple><advanced>Steel is a mixture of several metals (this is called an alloy) but most of it is iron.</advanced><advanced>Something made of pure iron is softer than steel because the atoms can slip over one another. If other atoms like carbon are added, they are different from iron atoms and stop the iron atoms from sliding apart so easily. This makes the metal stronger and harder.</advanced><advanced>Althought steel is stronger and lighter than iron, it is often not strong or light enough for use in most rockets</advanced></model><model><simple>Aluminium</simple><advanced>Aluminum is a chemical element. It is the most abundant metal, and is known for its resistance to corrosion and its light weight.</advanced><advanced> Aluminum, however, melts at the high reentry temperatures. So, if a rocket needs to come back to Earth (like the Space Shuttle), heat shield tiles are added</advanced></model><model><simple>Titanium</simple><advanced>Titanium is a very strong metal. It is chemical element number 22 on the periodic table </advanced><advanced>Titanium is used for making the strongest and lightest parts of fighter jets, aircraft, and rockets</advanced><advanced>However, it can burn at high temperatures, and titanium dust is extremely flammable. </advanced></model><model><simple>Carbon composite</simple><advanced> It has the highest compressive strength of all the reinforcing materials (composites), and it has a high strength to weight ratio and low coefficient of thermal expansion</advanced><advanced> The density of carbon fiber is also much lower than the density of steel.</advanced><advanced>Carbon fiber is in the form of several thousand long, thin strands of material that is composed of mostly carbon atoms.</advanced></model><model><simple>Spring</simple><advanced>Spring propelled rockets use the potential energy stored in a compressed spring, to form kinetic energy, and launch the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These types of rockets are easy to make at home, however, they do not go very high!</advanced></model><model><simple>Compressed air</simple><advanced>Compressed air rockets use the pressure of a compressed air tank, to form kinetic energy launching the rocket up</advanced><advanced>These systems are more powerful then spring powered ones, however, they </advanced><advanced></advanced></model><model><simple>Solid fuel</simple><advanced>Solid rocket fuels are those in which the fuel and oxidiser compounds are already combined.</advanced><advanced>Most use an aluminium powder as the fuel and an ammonium perchlorate as the oxidiser, while an iron powder is used as a catalyst for the reaction.</advanced><advaced>Solid fuels are generally used more for the initial launch sequence, when the speed needs to be at its maximum, whereas liquid fuels are used later so the speed can be adjusted to get the rocket’s payload on to the right trajectory.</advaced></model><model><simple>Liquid fuel</simple><advanced>Liquid propellants separate fuel and oxidisers and the two are combined in a combustion chamber where they burn and are ﬁred out from the base of the rocket.</advanced><advanced>iquid fuels are further subcategorised into either petroleum, cryogens or hypergols.</advanced><advanced>Petroleum is fuel derived from crude oil and hydrocarbons, it consists of a highly refined kerosene mixed with liquid oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Cryogens are those stored at very low temperatures (such as liquid hydrogen)</advanced><advanced>Hypergols are able to self-ignite on contact between the fuel and the oxidiser.  These fuels simply needs nitric acid in order to ignite and are frequently used for propulsion when out in space.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravity</simple><advanced>Gravity is one of the four fundamental forces of nature, althought it is the weakest of these four forces, it is important to life on Earth and the structure of the universe.</advanced><advanced>Everything that has matter generates gravity, from a grain of sand to the largest objects in the universe. The larger an object is, the stronger its force</advanced><advanced>In order for a rocket to reach space, the force it exerts up, must be more than the force of gravity pulling it down</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Third Law</simple><advanced>Rocket fuel works on the basis of Newton’s Third Law of Motion, which states that ‘every action is accompanied by an equal and opposite reaction'.</advanced><advanced>By ﬁring fuel out the back of a rocket, the force propels it upwards with acceleration equal to the force at which the fuel is expelled.</advanced><quiz>This law states that every action has an equal and opposite reaction</quiz><quiz>Rockets are based on this law, it is what causes the rocket to be pushed up, when the exahust is pushed down</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons Second Law</simple><advanced>Newtons Second Law says that the acceleration of an object produced by a net (total) applied force is directly related to the magnitude of the force, the same direction as the force, and inversely related to the mass of the object</advanced><quiz>This law states that aceleration is directly related to the force, and inversly related to the mass of an object</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that it is harder to push heavier things </quiz></model><model><simple>Space</simple><advanced>Space begins about 100 km (62 miles) above Earth's surface.</advanced><advanced>However, the space around Earth is not empty. There are many artificial satellites, about 5000, these are used for gather information, navigation, and communication amoung other things.</advanced><advanced>There is also a large amount of space junk. Space junk is any human-made object orbiting Earth that no longer serves a useful purpose. Scientists estimate there are about 500,000 pieces of space junk today.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Newtons First Law</simple><advanced>Newtons First Law says that an object at rest tends to stay at rest, and an object in motion tends to stay in motion, with the same direction and speed</advanced><advanced>For example, if you watch videos of astronauts in space, you will notice that their tools float, and they wont move unless the astronaut pushes or pulls it, at which point it will keep moving until it is stopped</advanced><quiz>This law states that an object will stay at rest, or continue in motion unless acted on by an external force</quiz><quiz>It is because of this law that objects stay in one spot in space</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Slower</simple><quiz>If a rocket was launched from jupiter, (where the gravity is higher) would it be faster, slower orthe same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Faster</simple><quiz>If the same rocket was launched from the moon (where gravity is lower) would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a lighter material was used for the rocket body would it be faster, slower, or the same speed?</quiz><quiz>If a you push a small object with some force, and then push a larger object with the same force, will the larger object go faster, slower or the same speed?</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Same speed</simple><quiz>If a rocket runs out of fuel in space, but it is moving foward, in 1000 years, will it be travelling faster, slower or at the same speed?</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Kinetic and potential energy" topics="28" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Welcome</simple><advanced>Create your own Gold Ruberg machine to learn about the different types of energies, and how they can be transfered from one form to another</advanced><advanced>You can add objects from the menu on the left, when you are ready, click play!</advanced><advanced>You can also choose from the prebuilt models, to get some ideas for your own machines</advanced><advanced>Want to put your machine to the test? Click the submit button to enter it into the weekly Gold Ruberg competition, and compete for prizes!</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal energy</simple><advanced>Matter is made up of particles or molecules. These molecules move (or vibrate) constantly.</advanced><advanced>A rise in the temperature of matter makes the particles vibrate faster. Thermal energy is what we call energy that comes from the temperature of matter. The hotter the substance, the more its molecules vibrate, and therefore the higher its thermal energy.</advanced><advanced>However, thermal energy and temprature are not the same thing. The temperature of an object is to do with how hot or cold it is and is measured in degrees Celsius (°C). Meanwhile thermal energy depends on the number of molecules, and the temprature, it is meassure in Jolues </advanced><advanced>To understand the differnece, consider the following example: </advanced><advanced>A swimming pool at 40°C is at a lower temperature than a cup of tea at 90°C. However, the swimming pool contains a lot more water. Therefore, the pool has more thermal energy than the cup of tea even though the tea is hotter than the water in the pool.</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic energy</simple><advanced>All moving things have kinetic energy. It is energy possessed by an object due to its motion or movement. </advanced><advanced>These include very large things, like planets, and very small ones, like atoms. The heavier a thing is, and the faster it moves, the more kinetic energy it has.</advanced><advnaced></advnaced></model><model><simple>Mechanical energy</simple><advanced>Mechanical energy is often confused with Kinetic and Potential Energy.</advanced><advanced>Before that, we need to understand the word ‘Work’.</advanced><advanced>‘Work’ is done when a force acts on an object to cause it to move, change shape, displace, or do something physical.</advanced><advanced>For work to be done, the object must move, if you push as hard as you can on a wall, althought you exert a force, you do no work. However, if you move a pencil, althought the force used is smaller, you still do more work, because the pencil moved</advanced><advanced>Mechanical energy is the sum of kinetic and potential energy in an object that is used to do work. In other words, it is energy in an object due to its motion or position, or both.</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational energy</simple><advanced> Gravitational Potential energy is stored in the height of the object. Any time that a heavy object is kept high up, a force or power is likely to be holding it up there.</advanced><advanced>Therefore, the higher the object, and the heavier it is, the more gravitational energy it has</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic energy</simple><advanced>Each time energy is transferred into an object, two things happen. It is either used to do work, or it is stored in the object. If it is stored, the object is given potential energy that can be released to do work.</advanced><advanced>Elastic energy is energy stored in stretched or compressed elastic materials.</advanced></model><model><simple>Elastic to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Elastic energy can be converted into kinetic energy. In this case the potential elastic energy stored in the spring is converted into kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>In this case, the total mechanical energy of the system remains the same, as no extra energy was created or destoryed, it only changed forms</advanced></model><model><simple>Gravitational to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Gravitational potential energy can be converted into kinetic energy, or motion.</advanced><advanced>As an object begins to fall, its gravitational energy decreases, but at the same time its kinetic energy increases. In this way, the total energy of the system remains the same</advanced></model><model><simple>Thermal to kinetic energy</simple><advanced>Thermal energy can be transfered into kinetic energy. The thermal energy causes the molecules in the surrounding area to vibrate and move more, this in turn can push on other objects, causing kinetic energy</advanced><advanced>As the molecules push on some object, or on eachother, they begin to cool. In this way the thermal energy decreases, but the kinetic energy increases the same amount</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to elastic energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into elastic potential energy. This can happen for exmaple when a ball falls on a spring, and compresses it. </advanced><advanced>In this case, the kinetic energy of the ball is 0, as is the spring. However, the same amount of energy is still in the system, except it is now stored as potential energy in the spring</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to gravitational energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into gravitation energy. For example, when you throw a ball in the air as it rises it begins to slow, until eventually it stops and begins to fall again</advanced><advanced>as the ball rises, its kinetic energy begins to become stored in gravitational potential energy. When the ball is at the top of its path, the kinetic energy is 0 (its not moving), this means that all the energy in the system is stored in gravitational potential energy</advanced></model><model><simple>Kinetic to thermal energy</simple><advanced>Kinetic energy can be transffered into thermal energy.</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Thermal energy" topics="2" level="5" index="63" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Waves" topics="29" level="5" index="95" score="0"><model><simple>Waves</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about basic wave terminology</advanced><advanced>
            There are lots of waves all around us in everyday life. Sound is a type of wave that moves through matter and then vibrates our eardrums so we can hear.
            Light is a special kind of wave that is made up of photons. You can drop a rock into a pond and see waves form in the water. We even use waves (microwaves) to cook our food
          </advanced><advanced>Waves can be divided into various categories depending on their characteristics. All waves can be categorized as either mechanical or electromagnetic.</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Mechanical waves</simple><advanced>Mechanical waves are waves that require a medium. This means that they have to have some sort of matter to travel through. These waves travel when molecules in the medium collide with each other passing on energy.</advanced><advanced>One example of a mechanical wave is sound. Sound can travel through air, water, or solids, but it can't travel through a vacuum. It needs the medium to help it travel. Other examples include water waves, seismic waves, and waves traveling through a spring.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave requries a medium</quiz><quiz>Sound waves are an exmaple of this type of wave</quiz><quiz>This type of wave cannot travel throught a vacuum</quiz><quiz>Water waves is this type of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Electromagnetic waves</simple><advanced>Electromagnetic waves are waves that can travel through a vacuum (empty space). They don't need a medium or matter.</advanced><advanced>They travel through electrical and magnetic fields that are generated by charged particles. Examples of electromagnetic waves include light, microwaves, radio waves, and X-rays.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave doesn't require a medium</quiz><quiz>Microwaves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Radio waves are this type of wave</quiz><quiz>Light is this kind of wave</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Travelling waves</simple><advanced>Another way to describe a wave is by the direction that its disturbance is traveling. We can categorize waves into two categories, transverse and longitudinal waves</advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Transverse waves</simple><advanced>Transverse waves are waves where the disturbance moves perpendicular to the direction of the wave.</advanced><advanced>You can think of the wave moving left to right, while the disturbance moves up and down. One example of a transverse wave is a water wave where the water moves up and down as the wave passes through the ocean.</advanced><quiz>This type of wave causes disturbances perpendicualr to the direction of the wave</quiz><quiz>Water waves move in this type of way</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Longitudinal waves</simple><advanced>Longitudinal waves are waves where the disturbance moves in the same direction as the wave.</advanced><advanced>One example of this is a wave moving through a stretched out slinky or spring. If you compress one portion of the slinky and let go, the wave will move left to right. At the same time, the disturbance (which is the coils of the springs moving), will also move left to right.</advanced><advanced> Another classic example of a longitudinal wave is sound. As sound waves propagate through a medium, the molecules collide with each other in the same direction as the sound is moving.</advanced><quiz>Sound waves move in this type of way</quiz><quiz>This type of wave causes a disturbance in the same direction as the wave</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //6
          <simple>Amplitude</simple><advanced>The amplitude of a wave is a measure of the displacement of the wave from its rest position, in other words it is how high/low the wave goes</advanced><advanced>In the case of water waves this can be thought of as the height of the wave, the higher the wave the larger the amplitude</advanced><advanced>The amplitude is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave. For example, when looking at a sound wave, the amplitude will measure the loudness of the sound. The energy of the wave also varies in direct proportion to the amplitude of the wave.</advanced><quiz>This is the measure of the displacement of the wave</quiz><quiz>This can be thought of as the height of the wave</quiz><quiz>This is a measure of the strength or intensity of the wave</quiz><quiz>This represents the loudness for sound waves</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //7
          <simple>Wavelength</simple><advanced>The wavelength of a wave is the distance between two corresponding points on back-to-back cycles of a wave.</advanced><advanced>This can be measured between two crests of a wave or two troughs of a wave. The wavelength is usually represented in physics by the Greek letter lambda (λ).</advanced><advanced>In the term of water waves this can be thought of as how "long" the waves are</advanced><quiz>This measures the distance between two corresponding points on back to back cycles of a wave</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //8
          <simple>Frequency and Period</simple><advanced>The frequency of a wave is the number of times per second that the wave cycles. Frequency is measured in Hertz or cycles per second. The frequency is often represented by the lower case "f."</advanced><advanced>The period of the wave is the time between wave crests. The period is measured in time units such as seconds. The period is usually represented by the upper case "T."</advanced><advanced>The period and frequency are closely related to each other. The period equals 1 over the frequency and the frequency is equal to one over the period. They are reciprocals of each other</advanced></model><model section="2">
          //9
          <simple>Velocity of a Wave</simple><advanced>Another important property of a wave is the speed of propagation. This is how fast the disturbance of the wave is moving. </advanced><advanced>The speed of mechanical waves depends on the medium that the wave is traveling through. For example, sound will travel at a different speed in water than in air.</advanced><advanced>velocity = frequency * wavelength or v = f * λ</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Mixtures" topics="4" level="5" index="65" score="0"></lesson> //difference between this and mixtures?
      <lesson name="Classification" topics="8" level="5" index="68" score="0"><model><simple>Classifcation</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the history of taxonomy, and how we calssify all living things</advanced></model><model><simple>Carolus Linnaeus</simple><advanced>Back in the 18th century, a Swedish man named Carolus Linnaeus thought it was important to organize living things, and he developed a system to do just that. </advanced><advanced>His system first only contained plants, however, he quickly expanded it to include all living organisms. We still use the essence of his system today. Scientists are constantly refining the system based on new knowledge. </advanced><advanced>Putting animals in order like this is called taxonomy. The taxonomists — people who name animals — use a book called the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, or ICZN, to tell them the rules for classifying animals.</advanced></model><model><simple>Linnaeus’s system</simple><advanced> His system has seven levels: Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, and Species</advanced><advanced>Every animal on the planet, down to the most microscopic creature you can imagine, can be classified according to this system.</advanced><advanced>An easy way to remember the order is to use the memonic: King Phillip, come out, for goodness’ sake!</advanced></model><model><simple>Kingdom</simple><advanced>Generally, scientists agree there are six kingdoms. The animal kingdom (called Kingdom Animalia) is just one of those. </advanced><advanced>The others are Achaebacteria, Eubacteria, Protists, Fungi and Plants.</advanced><advanced>Originally, Linnaeus only identified two kingdoms: plant and animal. Some scientists think that viruses should have their own kingdom, but currently they are not included under this system.</advanced></model><model><simple>Phylum</simple><advanced>Within the animal kingdom, the animals are divided into more than 30 phyla (which is the plural of “phylum”). </advanced><advanced>Some of the better known phyla are Phylum Chordata and Phylum Arthropoda. Phylum Chordata is the one humans and all animals with backbones are in.</advanced><advanced>Phylum Arthropoda contains insects, spiders and other animals with segmented bodies, like shrimp.  Arthropods have their skeletons on the outside of their bodies (think of the hard shell of a lobster) and other characteristics in common. </advanced></model><model><simple>Class</simple><advanced>The third level of classification is class. For example, Phylum Chordata has classes in it like birds, mammals (Mammalia) and reptiles.</advanced></model><model><simple>Order</simple><advanced>The next level, or rank, is order. Orders are smaller groups within the different classes.</advanced><advanced>Different orders include Lepidoptera and Carnivora. Lepidoptera is the order of moths and butterflies. Carnivora is the order within Mammalia that has the most diversity in animal size.</advanced></model><model><simple>Family</simple><advanced>The fifth rank of classification is family. </advanced></model><model><simple>Genus</simple><advanced>Genus the second-to-last rank, and a genus may have only one or two animals in it. If animals are in the same genus, they are really closely related. </advanced><advanced> In fact, you may not be able to tell them apart just by looking at them! When we write the name of the genus, we capitalize it and italicize it.</advanced><advanced>For example, the genus of dogs (and wolves, too!) is Canis.</advanced></model><model><simple>Species</simple><advanced>If animals can breed together successfully, they are a species. When an animal is called by its scientific name, then that means it is being identified by its genus and species. </advanced><advanced> We use a lowercase letter and italics for the species. </advanced><advanced>For example, the scientific name of dogs is Canis familiaris; however, the scientific name of wolves is Canis lupus.</advanced></model></lesson><lesson name="Scientific Names" topics="9" level="5" index="69" score="0"><model section="1"><simple>Scientific Names</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about common scientific names </advanced></model><model><simple>Modern Humans</simple><advanced>Homo sapiens</advanced><quiz>Homo sapiens</quiz></model><model><simple>African elephant</simple><advanced>Loxodonta africana</advanced><quiz>Loxodonta africana</quiz></model><model><simple>Black rat</simple><advanced>Rattus rattus</advanced><quiz>Rattus rattus</quiz></model><model><simple>Cat</simple><advanced>Felis domesticus</advanced><quiz>Felis domesticus</quiz></model><model><simple>Dog</simple><advanced>Canis lupus familiaris</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus familiaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Horse</simple><advanced>Equus caballus</advanced><quiz>Equus caballus</quiz></model><model><simple>Lion</simple><advanced>Panthera leo</advanced><quiz>Panthera leo</quiz></model><model><simple>Wolf</simple><advanced>Canis lupus</advanced><quiz>Canis lupus</quiz></model><model><simple>Apple</simple><advanced>Malus pumila</advanced><quiz>Malus pumila</quiz></model><model><simple>Carrot</simple><advanced>Daucas carota</advanced><quiz>Daucas carota</quiz></model><model><simple>Lemon</simple><advanced>Citrus limonium</advanced><quiz>Citrus limonium</quiz></model><model><simple>Lettuce</simple><advanced>Lactuca sativa</advanced><quiz>Lactuca sativa</quiz></model><model><simple>Potato</simple><advanced>Solanum tubersum</advanced><quiz>Solanum tubersum</quiz></model><model><simple>Watermelon</simple><advanced>Citrullus vulgaris</advanced><quiz>Citrullus vulgaris</quiz></model><model><simple>Wheat</simple><advanced>Triticum aestivum</advanced><quiz>Triticum aestivum</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Energy Sources" topics="42" level="5" index="76" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Biochemistry" topics="30" level="5" index="87" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Animal Cell" topics="14" level="5" index="71" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plant Cell" topics="15" level="5" index="72" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Anatomy and physiology" topics="31" level="5" index="88" score="0"><model><simple>Heart</simple><advanced>The Heart's function is to pump blood throughout the body</advanced><advanced>The Heart is considered a muscle</advanced><advanced>The heart consists of four different chambers: the left atrium, the right atrium, the left ventricle and the right ventricle.</advanced><quiz>This organ is made up of four different chambers</quiz></model><model><simple>Brain</simple><advanced>The Brain allows us to think, store memories, analyze and make judgments while at the same time controlling other areas automatically, such as breathing.</advanced><advanced>The human brain weighs 3 pounds and is made up of 60% fat. The brain consists of the cerebrum, the brainstem, and the cerebellum.</advanced><advanced>The cerebrum: this is responsible for a number of things like speech, motion, it also controls movement and learning it’s the largest part of the brain.</advanced><advanced>The cerebellum: its main function is for helping with muscle movements, posture and balance</advanced>\
          <advanced>The brainstem: plays a really important function by connecting the cerebrum and cerebellum to your spinal cord. It automatically looks after many of our bodies function like body temperature, digestion, heart rate and even things like sneezing and coughing.</advanced><quiz>This organ controls all of our bodys vital functions</quiz></model><model><simple>Lungs</simple><advanced>Blood runs through our body, goes to the lungs to pick up oxygen from the air we breathe in and then drops off carbon dioxide, which we breathe out.</advanced><advanced>The average adult individual breathes almost 11,000 liters of air every single day.</advanced><advanced>The lungs have special little hairs in tubes in your lungs that move up and out. This helps the special cells that produce mucus. Mucus in the lungs is also specialized as it catches bacteria, dirt and dust that you breathe in as well as bacteria in the air.</advanced><quiz>This organ supplies blood with oxygen, and removes carbon dioxide</quiz></model><model><simple>Liver</simple><advanced>The liver is involved in almost every vital function of the body, such as making and storing energy; producing proteins vital for body function; processing drugs, and playing a vital role in immune function. </advanced><advanced>Your liver is the second largest organ (after the skin), it weights about 3 pounds</advanced><advanced>It's the only organ that can completly regenerate, it only needs 25% of the orignial tissue, and can regrow in less than two weeks</advanced><quiz>It is the second largest organ in the body</quiz></model><model><simple>Kidney</simple><advanced>Kidneys are two bean shaped organs, that are responsible for creating urine</advanced><advanced>Kidneys make hormones. The two most important ones that it makes are erythropoetin and renin.</advanced><advanced>The kidney's most important work is keeping homeostasis. Homeostasis means that the body keeps a stable environment inside itself</advanced><quiz>This organ is important in keeping homeostasis</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Fossils" topics="19" level="5" index="78" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plant reproduction" topics="34" level="5" index="89" score="0"><model><simple>Seed</simple><advanced>Inside a seed is an embryo, which is a tiny plant, and the endosperm, which are small leaves which supply the embryo food. The outside of the seed has a seed coat, which protects the embryo from injury or drying out.</advanced><advanced>All seeds need moisture, oxygen and the right temperature to germinate, or grow. Until they have these conditions, the seed remains dormant and does nothing.</advanced><quiz>This is where all plants start their lives</quiz></model><model><simple>Male flower</simple><advanced> Pollen is the male cell - it's the yellow dust made on the stamen, or male reproductive part, of the flower. </advanced></model><model><simple>Female Flower</simple><advanced>The female part is called the pistil, which contains the ovaries that produce eggs, and it's located in the center of the flower.</advanced><advanced>The pistil also contains the stigma, a sticky bulb that the pollen attaches itself to.</advanced></model></lesson> //add this
      <lesson name="Photosynthesis" topics="35" level="5" index="90" score="0"><model><simple>Carbon Dioxide</simple><advanced>Carbon dioxide is a gas that is present in the air.</advanced><advanced>Plants collect carbon dioxide through tiny holes called stomates.</advanced><advaned>Carbon dioxide is then combined with water and oxygen in a process known as photosynthesis</advaned><quiz>This gas is needed to complete photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Energy from the Sun</simple><advanced>Sunlight is absorbed by a green chemical in the leaves, called chlorophil</advanced><advanced>The energy from the sun is used to split the water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen</advanced><quiz>This source of energy is required for photosynthesis</quiz></model><model><simple>Oxygen</simple><advanced>During the process of photosynthesis, stomates are used to expel a gas called oxygen.</advanced><advanced>Oxygen is very important for animals like humans – we need it to breathe!</advanced><quiz>This is biproduct of photosynthesis is expelled by the plant</quiz></model><model><simple>Glucose</simple><advanced>Glucose is a type of sugar, that the plant uses as energy to grow, and reproduce</advanced><advanced>Glucose is produced throught photosynthesis, the word equation would be: Carbon Dioxide + Water + Light Energy = Glucose + Oxygen</advanced><quiz>This is what the plant produces throught photosynthesis, which it uses to grow and reproduce</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Ecosystems" topics="41" level="5" index="73" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Ecology" topics="16" level="5" index="74" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Ecological interactions" topics="36" level="5" index="91" score="0"><model><simple>Ecological interaction</simple><advacned>In this module you will learn about the different interactions in a food web and food chain</advacned></model><model section="1"><simple>Food chain</simple><advanced>Every living plant and animal must have energy to survive. Plants rely on the soil, water, and the sun for energy. Animals rely on plants as well as other animals for energy.</advanced><advanced>In an ecosystem, plants and animals all rely on each other to live. Scientists sometimes describe this dependence using a food chain or a food web.</advanced><advanced>A food chain describes how different organisms eat each other, starting out with a plant and ending with an animal. </advanced></model><model section="1"><simple>Food Web</simple><advanced>In any ecosystem there are many food chains and, generally, most plants and animals are part of several chains. When you draw all the chains together you end up with a food web.</advanced><quiz>This describes an ecosystem with many food chains</quiz></model><model section="1"><simple>Trophic Levels</simple><advanced>Sometimes scientists describe each level in a food web with a trophic level. Here are the five trophic levels:</advanced><advanced>   Level 1: Plants (producers)</advanced><advanced>Level 2: Animals that eat plants or herbivores (primary consumers)</advanced><advanced>Level 3: Animals that eat herbivores (secondary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 4: Animals that eat carnivores (tertiary consumers, carnivores)</advanced><advanced>Level 5: Animals at the top of the food chain are called apex predators. Nothing eats these animals.</advanced><quiz>These levels describe each level in a food web</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //kelp and plankton
          <simple>Producers </simple><advanced>Plants are producers. This is because they produce energy for the ecosystem.</advanced><advanced>They do this because they absorb energy from sunlight through photosynthesis. They also need water and nutrients from the soil, but plants are the only place where new energy is made.</advanced></model><model section="2"><simple>Primary Consumers</simple> //crab
          <advanced>Animals are consumers. This is because they don't produce energy, they just use it up.</advanced><advanced> Animals that eat plants are called primary consumers or herbivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat plants</quiz><quiz>Another name for these animals is herbivores</quiz></model><model section="2">
          // squid, krill
          <simple>Secondary Consumers</simple><advanced>Animals that eat other animals are called secondary consumers or carnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat herbivores.</quiz><quiz>Another name for these consumers is carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //penguin, walrus, seal, seagull
          <simple>Tertiary Consumer</simple><advanced> If a carnivore eats another carnivore, it is called a tertiary consumer.</advanced><quiz>These are animals that eat other carnivores</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Omnivore</simple> //fish
          <advanced>Some animals play both roles, eating both plants and animals. They are called omnivores.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat both plants and animals</quiz></model><model section="2"><simple>Decomposers</simple> //plankton
          <advanced>Decomposers eat decaying matter (like dead plants and animals). They help put nutrients back into the soil for plants to eat. </advanced><advanced>Examples of decomposers are worms, bacteria, and fungi.</advanced><quiz>These animals eat decaying matter</quiz><quiz>Worms, bacteria and fungi belong to this group</quiz></model><model section="2">
          //killer whale, whale
          <simple>Apex preditor</simple><advanced>Apex predators are predators with no natural predators of their own. They are at the top of their food chain.</advanced><quiz>These animals are at the top of their food chain</quiz><quiz>These animals have not preditors  of their own</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Natural resources and human impacts" topics="37" level="5" index="92" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Rocks and minerals" topics="18" level="5" index="77" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" index="93" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Topographic maps" topics="39" level="5" inex="94" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Water cycle" topics="21" level="5" index="80" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" score="0"><model><simple>Plate Tectonics</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about plate tectonics, their different types, and how they shape our world</advanced></model><model><simple>Divergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In some places, the plates are pulling apart. New crust is pushed up from below. </advanced><advanced> These are called divergent boundaries and they create rifts or valleys.</advanced><advanced>Large lakes sometimes form in rifts.</advanced><quiz>These places create rifts or valleys</quiz></model><model><simple>Convergent boundaries</simple><advanced>In other places the plates are pushing against each other, creating mountains</advanced><advanced> Sometimes one crust is dragged beneath – or subducted – below another one</advanced><advanced>Ocean plates are heavier than continental plates so these plates are always dragged beneath.</advanced><quiz>These boundaries create mountains</quiz></model><model><simple>Transform boundaries</simple><advanced>A transform boundary happens when plates slide past each other but neither collide nor rip apart.</advanced><advanced>The San Andreas Fault in California is a transform boundary.</advanced><quiz>At these boundaries, plates slide past each other</quiz></model></lesson><lesson name="Weather and climate" topics="20" level="5" index="79" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Astronomy" topics="22" level="5" index="81" score="0"></lesson></subject>
    <subject name="Other">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="8">
    <subject name="math">
      <lesson name="number theory" topics="114,115,15,16,17,18" level="5" index="4" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="integers" topics="15,16,17,18,117,98,99,60,100,101" level="5" index="35" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="decimals" topics="121,126" level="5" index="28" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="operations with fractions" topics="7,20,54,42" level="5" index="39" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="fractions, decimals and percents" topics="77,78,79,80,81" index="38" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="operations with rational numbers" topics="" index="40" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="exponents and roots" topics="27,120,88,89" level="5" index="36" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="scientific notation" topics="39,40,41,75,76,102" level="5" index="41" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="ratios and rates and proportions" topics="92,93,94,12,52,19" level="5" index="31" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="proportional relationships" topics="" level="5" index="37" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="percents" topics="8,49,50,13,95,96,67,97" level="5" index="32" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="units of measurement" topics="55,56,57,45,74,112,122" index="20" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="problem solving" topics="" level="5" index="13" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132,142,151,152" level="5" index="15" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="two-dimensional figures" topics="141,142,143,144,62" level="5" index="21" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="transformations and congruence" topics="" level="5" index="0" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="transformations and similarity" topics="" level="5" index="0" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="pythagorean theorem" topics="" level="5" index="42" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="three-dimensional figures" topics="149,150" level="5" index="23" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="geometic measurement" topics="-1" level="5" index="43" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="number sequences" topics="21,22,71,72,47" level="5" index="14" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="expressions and properties" topics="68,64,65,29,51,14" level="5" index="16" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="one-variable equations" topics="29,38,64,65,68,51,66,44,43,46,48,124" level="5" index="33" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="linear functions" topics="82,83,145,146,147,148" level="5" index="44" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138,134,135,136,139" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="statistics and probability" topics="58,63,33,34,35,36,37" level="5" index="18" score="0"></lesson>
    </subject>
    <subject name="science">
      <lesson name="Science practices and tools" topics="23" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Designing experiments" topics="24" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Engineering practices" topics="25" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Matter and mass" topics="1" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Atoms and molecules" topics="5" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Chemical reactions" topics="26" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Velocity, acceleration, and forces" topics="27" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Kinetic and potential energy" topics="28" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Thermal energy" topics="2" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Waves" topics="29" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Solutions" topics="4" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Classification and scientific names" topics="9" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Biochemistry" topics="30" level="5" score="0"> //ok, so for this one, put it in models, just get the cell model, and have the images of the protiens and all that as particle systems that they can click on
        <model section="1"><simple>Biochemistry</simple><advanced>In this module you will learn about the basics of carbohydrates, lipids, protiens, and nucleic acid, as well as celular respiration</advanced></model><model><simple>Carbohydrate</simple><advanced>Carbohydrates are chemical compounds that contain only oxygen, hydrogen and carbon. </advanced><advanced>They are made up of joined-up sugars. Sugars have the general formula Cm(H2O)n, and are also known as saccharides.</advanced><advanced>Certain carbohydrates are an important storage and transport form of energy in most organisms, including plants and animals.</advanced><advanced>Carbohydrates are very good for energy, but, if a person eats more than needed, the extra is changed into fat.</advanced><quiz>These molecules are very good for energy, however if too much of them are eaten, they are changed into fat</quiz><quiz>These molecules are made of joined-up sugars</quiz></model><model><simple>Lipids</simple><advanced>A lipid is a type of organic molecule found in living things. It is oily or waxy. Fats are made from lipid molecules.</advanced><advanced>Sources of lipid can be found in algae, seeds, meat, cheese, butter and fish. </advanced><advanced>Lipids are long chains of carbon and hydrogen molecules. Lipids are classified as simple and complex. Examples of complex molecules could be steroids or phospholipids.</advanced><advanced>A very important biological function of lipids is as lipid bilayers, the basis of many cell membranes. Another function of lipids is to serve as an energy reserve.</advanced><advanced>In summary, lipids are a group of naturally occurring molecules that include fats, waxes, sterols, fat-soluble vitamins (such as vitamins A, D, E, and K), glycerides, phospholipids, and others. The main biological functions of lipids include storing energy, signalling, and acting as components of cell membranes.</advanced><quiz>These molecules naturally occure in fats, waxes and fat-soluble vitamins</quiz><quiz>These molecules are classified as either simple or complex</quiz><quiz>The main functions of this molelcule include signalling, storing energy, and building the cell membrane</quiz></model><model><simple>Protiens</simple><advanced>Proteins are long-chain molecules built from small units known as amino acids. They are joined together with peptide bonds.</advanced><advanced>Proteins are essential to all cells. proteins take part in virtually every process in cells</advanced><advanced>Proteins do different things depending on their shape. They can be found in meat or muscle. They are used for growth and repair, making tissue cells and used for strengthening the bones.</advanced><advanced>There are four things that determine what a protein will do. The first is the order of the amino acids. he second is the little twists in the chain. The third is how the entire thing is folded up. The fourth is whether it is made up of different sub-units</advanced><quiz>These molecules are made up of small units known as amino acids</quiz><quiz>These molecules are found in large numbers in meat and muscle</quiz><quiz>These molecules are used for growth, repair, making tissue cells and strengthening bones amoung others</quiz></model><model><simple>Nucleic Acids</simple><advanced>Nucleic acids are large molecules where genetic information is stored. There are two types of nucleic acids: deoxyribonucleic acid, better known as DNA and ribonucleic acid, better known as RNA.</advanced><advanced>Nucleic acids allow organisms to transfer genetic information from one generation to the next. When a cell divides, its DNA is copied and passed from one cell generation to the next generation.</advanced><advanced>DNA is organized into chromosomes and found within the nucleus of our cells. Its function in any cell is to carry the sequence of bases which will be transcribed into RNA. RNA then has many function within the cell</advanced><quiz>These molecules are responsible for passing on genetic information</quiz><quiz>These molecules are used to create another important molecule known as RNA</quiz><quiz>These molecules are organized into chromosones</quiz></model><model><simple>Cellular respiration</simple><advanced>Cellular respiration is what cells do to break up sugars into a form that the cell can use as energy. </advanced><advanced>Cellular respiration takes in food and uses it to create ATP, a chemical which the cell uses for energy. Usually, this process uses oxygen, and is called aerobic respiration.</advanced><advanced>It also produces carbon dioxide as a waste product, which then enters the circulatory system. The carbon dioxide is taken to the lungs, where it is exchanged for oxygen.</advanced><advanced> When they don't get enough oxygen, the cells use anaerobic respiration, which doesn’t require oxygen. However, this process produces lactic acid, and is not as efficient as when oxygen is used. </advanced><advanced>The equation for this process is Glucose (sugar) + Oxygen → Carbon dioxide + Water + Energy (as ATP)</advanced><quiz>Every cell does this to produce energy</quiz></model></lesson>
      <lesson name="Animal Cell" topics="14" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Plant Cell" topics="15" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Anatomy and physiology" topics="31" level="5" score="0">
        <model>
          <simple>Heart</simple>
          <advanced>The Heart's function is to pump blood throughout the body</advanced>
          <advanced>The Heart is considered a muscle</advanced>
          <advanced>The heart consists of four different chambers: the left atrium, the right atrium, the left ventricle and the right ventricle.</advanced>
          <quiz>This organ is made up of four different chambers</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Brain</simple>
          <advanced>The Brain allows us to think, store memories, analyze and make judgments while at the same time controlling other areas automatically, such as breathing.</advanced>
          <advanced>The human brain weighs 3 pounds and is made up of 60% fat. The brain consists of the cerebrum, the brainstem, and the cerebellum.</advanced>
          <advanced>The cerebrum: this is responsible for a number of things like speech, motion, it also controls movement and learning it’s the largest part of the brain.</advanced>
          <advanced>The cerebellum: its main function is for helping with muscle movements, posture and balance</advanced>\
          <advanced>The brainstem: plays a really important function by connecting the cerebrum and cerebellum to your spinal cord. It automatically looks after many of our bodies function like body temperature, digestion, heart rate and even things like sneezing and coughing.</advanced><quiz>This organ controls all of our bodys vital functions</quiz></model>
        <model>
          <simple>Lungs</simple>
          <advanced>Blood runs through our body, goes to the lungs to pick up oxygen from the air we breathe in and then drops off carbon dioxide, which we breathe out.</advanced>
          <advanced>The average adult individual breathes almost 11,000 liters of air every single day.</advanced>
          <advanced>The lungs have special little hairs in tubes in your lungs that move up and out. This helps the special cells that produce mucus. Mucus in the lungs is also specialized as it catches bacteria, dirt and dust that you breathe in as well as bacteria in the air.</advanced>
          <quiz>This organ supplies blood with oxygen, and removes carbon dioxide</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Liver</simple>
          <advanced>The liver is involved in almost every vital function of the body, such as making and storing energy; producing proteins vital for body function; processing drugs, and playing a vital role in immune function. </advanced>
          <advanced>Your liver is the second largest organ (after the skin), it weights about 3 pounds</advanced>
          <advanced>It's the only organ that can completly regenerate, it only needs 25% of the orignial tissue, and can regrow in less than two weeks</advanced>
          <quiz>It is the second largest organ in the body</quiz>
        </model>
        <model>
          <simple>Kidney</simple>
          <advanced>Kidneys are two bean shaped organs, that are responsible for creating urine</advanced>
          <advanced>Kidneys make hormones. The two most important ones that it makes are erythropoetin and renin.</advanced>
          <advanced>The kidney's most important work is keeping homeostasis. Homeostasis means that the body keeps a stable environment inside itself</advanced>
          <quiz>This organ is important in keeping homeostasis</quiz>
        </model>
      </lesson>
      <lesson name="Genes to traits" topics="32" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Adaptations and natural selection" topics="33" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Fossils" topics="19" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Plant reproduction" topics="34" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Photosynthesis" topics="35" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Ecosystems" topics="41" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Ecology" topics="16" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Ecological interactions" topics="36" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Natural resources and human impacts" topics="37" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Rocks and minerals" topics="18" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Plate tectonics" topics="38" level="5" index="93" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Topographic maps" topics="39" level="5" inex="94" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Water cycle" topics="21" level="5" index="80" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="Weather and climate" topics="20" level="5" index="79" score="0"></lesson> //not done
      <lesson name="Astronomy" topics="22" level="5" index="81" score="0"></lesson></subject>
    <subject name="Other">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="9">
    <subject name="math">
      <lesson name="numbers" topics="15,16,17,18,98,99" level="5" index="35" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="operations" topics="16,17,18,117,54" level="5" index="40" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="ratios and rates and proportions" topics="92,93,94,12,52,19" level="5" index="31" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="percents" topics="8,49,50,13,95,96,67,97" level="5" index="32" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="geometry" topics="" level="5" index="46" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132,142,151,152" level="5" index="15" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="properties" topics="" level="5" index="23" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="exponents" topics="27,88,89,90,91" level="5" index="45" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="scientific notation" topics="39,40,41,75,76,102" level="5" index="41" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="problem solving" topics="" level="5" index="13" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="number sequences" topics="21,22,71,72,47" index="14" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="variable expressions and equations" topics="38,43,48" level="5" index="16" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="solve equations" topics="" level="5" index="33" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="single-variable inequalities" topics="69,70,123" level="5" index="47" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138,134,135,136,139" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="relations and functions" topics="" level="5" index="37" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="direct variation" topics="" level="5" index="48" score="0"></lesson> //not added
      <lesson name="linear functions" topics="82,83,145,146,147,148" level="5" index="44" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="systems of linear equations" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="monomials" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="polynomials" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson><lesson name="probability" topics="58,63" level="5" index="18" score="0"></lesson></subject>
    <subject name="science">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
    <subject name="Other">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="10">
    <subject name="math">
      <lesson name="numbers" topics="15,16,17,18" level="5" index="35" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="exponents" topics="27,90,91" level="5" index="45" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="scientific notation" topics="39,40,41,75,76,102" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="radical expressions" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="radical exponents" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="coordinate plane" topics="131,132,142,151,152" level="5" index="15" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="solve equations" topics="43" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="single-variable inequalities" topics="69,70,123" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="data and graphs" topics="133,137,138,134,135,136,139" level="5" index="17" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="relations and functions" topics="73" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="direct and inverse variation" topics="" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="linear functions" topics="82,83,145,146,147,148" level="5" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="systems of linear equations" topics="" level="5" index="49" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="monomials" topics="" level="5" index="50" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="polynomials" topics="" level="5" idnex="51" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="factoring" topics="" level="5" index="52" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="quadratic equations" topics="84,85,86" level="5" index="53" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="functions: linear, quadratic, exponential" topics="86,87" level="5" index="54" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="rational functions and expressions" topics="" level="5" index="55" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="circles in the coordinate plane" topics="" level="5" index="56" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="measurement" topics="" level="5" index="20" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="two-dimensional figures" topics="" level="5" index="21" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="three-dimensional figures" topics="149,150" level="5" index="23" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="congruent figures" topics="" level="5" index="57" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="triangles" topics="" level="5" index="58" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="right triangles" topics="" level="5" index="59" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="trigonometry" topics="" level="5" index="60" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="transformations" topics="" level="5" index="61" score="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="probability" topics="" level="5" index="18" score="0"></lesson>
    </subject>
    <subject name="science">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
    <subject name="Other">
      <score>100</score>
      <time>20</time>
    </subject>
  </grade>
  <grade number="Deep">
    <subject name="Public Speaking">
      <lesson name="School" module="school" index="97" eyeContact="0" fillerWords="0" gestures="0" tone="0" score="0" level="0" topics="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Job interview" module="school" index="98" eyeContact="0" fillerWords="0" gestures="0" tone="0" score="0" level="0" topics="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Informal meeting" module="school" index="99" eyeContact="0" fillerWords="0" gestures="0" tone="0" score="0" level="0" topics="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Formal meeting" module="school" index="100" eyeContact="0" fillerWords="0" gestures="0" tone="0" score="0" level="0" topics="0"></lesson>
      <lesson name="Company presentation" module="school" index="101" eyeContact="0" fillerWords="0" gestures="0" tone="0" score="0" level="0" topics="0"></lesson>
    </subject>
  </grade>
</grades>